music
music
Today I am honored to introduce today's speaker, Professor Xie Shiliang
今天我很榮幸地來介紹今天的講者謝世良教授
Professor Xie is an artist-scientist
謝教授是一個藝師科學家
He graduated from the Faculty of Medicine, National Yang Ming University
他是在國立陽明大學的醫學院醫學系畢業
Afterwards, he went to Oxfern University of Liukin University in the UK to obtain a Ph.D.
之後他到英國柳金大學奧克斯芬得到了博士學位
in immunology
是在免疫學的
Then I went to Stanford University in the United States to talk to a master of immunization there.
然後又到美國的史丹佛大學跟那邊的一位做免疫的大師
do PhD and research
做博士和研究
After returning to China, I went to Yangming University to talk to the Agricultural Federation
之後回國就到陽明大學跟農總
i am a professor there
我在那裡做教授
I have been making professors since I was a teaching assistant
從助教的時候一直生造教授
He also served as the director of the immunization center there
在那裡也曾經當過那邊的免疫中心的主任
And the director of Linchuan Medical Research Institute
還有林川醫學研究所的所長
In 2013, he was the former dean of the hospital
2013年的時候是獲得本院的前院長
Dean of Weng Jihui
翁極會院長
Recruited to Genome Research Center
延攬到基因體研究中心
Course Specific Fellows
當然特定研究員
Professor Xie has a wide range of interests
謝教授的興趣非常廣闊
It is important that your focus is still on the immune and inflammatory response
重要你重點還是在免疫跟發言反應
in the early days
在早期的時候
He's working on a molecule called DCR3
他對一個分子叫做DCR3
I think he just mentioned
我想他剛剛會提一下
interested in
有興趣
did a lot of fun there
在那裡做了很多的非常有趣
and some important discoveries
而且很重要的一些發現
He just shared with me
他剛才跟我分享一下
Some recent results
最近的一些成果
he's very exciting
他非常讓人興奮的
maybe he'll say something
也許他會講了一些
In addition, after arriving at the Chinese Medicine Hospital about a few years ago,
另外大概幾年前到了中醫院之後
He became interested in Tang Science
他就對在唐科學這方面產生了興趣
So he went into a
所以他就進到一個做了
Research on a condensin we call C-Type
我們叫C-Type的一個凝基素的研究
One of the lectins is C-Lac5
其中一個凝基素是C-Lac5
It's also his topic today
也是他今天的主題
From there he found that this was
從那邊他發現這個是
Dengue virus receptor
登革熱病毒的受體
Then he goes through this receptor
然後他會經過這個受體
dengue virus
登革熱病毒
This nucleic acid virus can cause some very serious reactions in our body
這個核酸的病毒會造成我們人體的一些很嚴重的反應
So he also found out that he did
所以他也發現他做了
If the virus can be combined with the receptor and can be inhibited
能夠把這個病毒跟受體結合的能夠抑制住的話
to suppress these reactions
就可以抑制這些反應
This article was published in the magazine "Domination"
這個文章在《Domination》這個雜誌裡面發表
received international attention
受到國際上的重視
also got some patents
也得到一些專利
this is indeed
這個確實是
It can be said that it has received a famous work
可以說是受到一個成名作了
But this was already
但這個之前就已經是
In this area has already received great attention
在這方面的領域已經是非常受重視了
He has received numerous awards for his words in Taiwan
他在台灣的話已經得到無數的獎項
including the Ministry of Science and Technology
其中包括科技部的
Should be a research award for contact research
應該是接觸研究的研究獎
Then Ministry of Education Academic Award
然後教育部的學術獎
Ministry of Education's National Award
教育部的國家獎座
Every year, one or two can get
每年就是一兩位能夠拿到
Contributions in Taiwan in addition to his own research
在台灣的貢獻除了在他自己研究之外
He also has the talent of this leadership
他也是有這個領導的這方面的才能
Then he was also responsible for Taiwan's immunology exchanges with the United States
然後也負責台灣的免疫學跟美國交流
Head of the American Society for Immunology
參加美國的免疫學會的負責人
so i think today we are very happy
所以我想今天我們非常高興
He was able to share with us some of his recent
他能夠跟我們分享他最近的一些
Academic research and achievements
學術上的研究跟成果
So let's welcome Professor Xie Xuechang
所以我們就來歡迎謝學長教授
First of all, I would like to thank Vice President Liu Bodong for his introduction
首先先感謝劉伯東副院長的介紹
Then I would also like to thank the Solemn Academy for inviting me here
然後也感謝莊嚴就院院本部邀請我來
Share the results of our research with you
跟各位分享我們研究的成果
Thanks
謝謝
I would like to thank all ladies and gentlemen and the students who came to perform
更感謝各位女士先生還有演到來的同學
Come to Academia Sinica at such a late hour
在這麼晚的時候還來中央研究院
We were very moved after listening to the speech
聽著演講我們是覺得非常的感動
I want to introduce this topic to you today
我今天要跟各位介紹這個題目
cytokine storm
細胞激素風暴
It's actually quite a coincidence
其實是非常一個偶然的
Because before everyone assumes you remember
因為在大家假設還記得
In 2003, Taiwan had this Sauce
2003年的時候台灣有這個Sauce
when Sauce comes
Sauce來的時候
Everyone should be impressed
大家應該印象還滿深刻
At that time, the hundred-page depression could not go out
那時候百頁蕭條也不能出門
I still remember one time I drove to the 101 hair line
我還記得有一次我開車到101發線
empty with no one
空蕩蕩都沒有人
so you know that flush is very big
所以你知道那個沖洗是非常的大的
Then our AA chief at the time
那在當時我們的機管局局長
Also one of our anti-kill Kazuo
也是我們抗殺一雄之一
Chief Arborist
叫樹藝人局長
I don't know if you have no impression
不曉得各位還沒有印象
At that time, the chief arborist called me
那時候樹藝人局長就打個電話給我
he just said
他就說
Professor Xie, you are a person doing immunology research in Taiwan
謝教授你是台灣做免疫學研究的人
Then you come and give us a speech saying
那你就來給我們一個演講說
How Cytoheptin Storm Produces
細胞七素風暴是怎麼產生的
i was young
我當時年紀輕
I just want to say that there is a network
就想要說有網路嘛
Although I don't do cytoheptin storm
雖然我不做細胞七素風暴
I'm going to look up books
我去查書
It's okay to study and give a speech, right?
念念書來演講總可以吧
I'll say without hesitation
我就毫不失所的就說
no problem
沒問題
After I finish speaking, I will
講完之後我就
I regret it
混上就後悔了
because i go back at night
因為我晚上回去
When I started to search the book, I found that
開始查書的時候發現說
This message is really lacking
這個訊息還真的滿少的
Where did this Cytoheptin come from?
這細胞七素到底怎麼來的
Although we all know the virus
雖然我們都知道病毒
how to produce heparin
如何去產生肝腦素
eliciting this immune response is clearly
引起這個免疫反應很清楚
But Cytoheptin is still not clear
但是細胞七素還真的不清楚
So a crisis is an opportunity
所以危機就是一個轉機
So from now on I want to say
所以從此我就想說
then i should explore
那我應該去探索
Why do viruses cause cytoheptin storms
為什麼病毒會引起細胞七素風暴
Why does it cause panic among humans
它為什麼會造成人類的恐慌
or cause death
或造成死亡
the most important thing is to say
那最重要是說
do we have a way
我們到底有沒有方法
to overcome this virus
來克服這病毒
cytogenetic storm
引起的細胞氣素風暴
So all this research because it's a chance call
所以這所有的研究都是因為它一個偶然的電話
then a bad decision
然後一個錯誤的決定
led to the research I did today
促成我今天做的這個研究
before the disease
那講到疾病之前
let's talk about
我們就先講到說
our body
我們身體
How to maintain a steady state
如何維持一個衡定狀態
And what is our relationship to the inflammatory response?
然後我們跟發炎反應的關係是什麼
A person in a so-called healthy state of our body
我們身體一個人所謂的健康狀態的人
Let's call it a school of literature
我們就把它稱為他是在一個文派
Those who study biology probably know
那學生物的同學大概都知道
In biology we call it home-news-stasis
在生物學上我們就叫做home-news-stasis
What about when stimulated by various reasons?
那當有各種不同的原因的刺激之後呢
Our bodies are dissatisfied with all kinds of receptors
我們身體不滿各式各樣子的感受器
You can call it a receptor
你可以稱為叫做感受器也好
It can also be called receptor in English
也可以英文叫做receptor也好
Or sensee is fine
或sensee也好都可以
Basically it feels the presence of these stimuli
基本上它就感受到這些刺激的存在
when stimulated
感受到刺激的時候
you get an inflammatory reaction
你就會產生發炎反應
In the end, tissue repair will be fine.
那最後呢 組織修復就好了
I think this is anytime
我想這個是隨時隨地
happens all the time
無時無刻的發生
Just like we now our environment is full of
就像我們現在我們環境充滿了
various bacterial viruses
各式各樣的細菌病毒
Especially now that many influenza viruses
尤其現在很多流行性感冒病毒
in contagion
在傳染
Many people have no symptoms
很多人是沒什麼症狀
because when your body feels its presence
因為你身體感受到它存在的時候
you have a little inflammation
你有一點發炎
What about after inflammation?
那發炎之後呢
The final purpose is to return to a constant state
最後的目的是要回到恆定狀態
So in a controllable
所以在一個可以控制的
under inflammatory reaction
發炎反應之下
we call the so-called
我們稱為所謂的
Physiological inflammatory response
生理性的發炎反應
What is the purpose of the physiological inflammatory response?
生理性的發炎反應的目的呢
it's trying to go back to what's called a constant state
它是想再回到所謂的恆定狀態
So in this state
所以這樣子的狀態之下呢
You don't have to go to the hospital to see a doctor
大家就不用去醫院去看醫生了
you just hurt
你就痛一痛
just drink some hot water and take a rest
喝熱水休息一下就好了
we're back to what's called a constant state
我們就回到所謂的恆定狀態
But what if our body
但假使呢我們身體
If this inflammatory response is so perfect
這個發炎反應都這麼完美的話
Then we don't need a hospital
那我們就不需要醫院了
You don't need to go to the doctor
大家也不用去看醫生
The doctor is out of work again
醫生又失業了
so we need to know
所以我們要知道
Why Inflammation Can Sometimes Cause Problems
發炎反應為什麼有時候會造成問題
So from doing this tell you guys
所以從這樣做告訴各位說
The inflammatory reaction is actually a
發炎反應其實它是一個
complex a vascular an inflammatory response
複雜的一個血管性的一個發炎反應
Because we are in Zhouzhiao
因為我們在周治澳
A characteristic of an inflammatory response is redness, swelling, heat, and pain
發炎反應的一個特徵就是紅腫熱痛
why is it red
那為什麼會紅
It is the increase of blood flow in our blood vessels
就是我們血管它的血流增加
it will be swollen
那另外會腫
It is the increase in the permeability of our blood vessel currency
就是我們血管幣的通透性增加
This is very important
這個很重要
That is to say, we usually have a lot of
也就是說我們平常很多的
fluid in blood vessels
液體是在血管內的
But when you have a lot of inflammation
但是當你大量的發炎之後
The permeability of your blood vessel coins will increase
你的血管幣的通透性會增加
So some liquid will come out
所以有一些液體就會跑出外面來
if you run outside
跑出外面的話
This tissue will swell
這個組織它就會產生腫脹
Inflammation that is in the area
那在地區的發炎
its swelling is fine
它的腫脹是沒什麼問題
It's just that the mouth may be swollen.
就是嘴巴可能就腫了一下
Then fatter people like me
然後像我這胖一點的人
It may be a little swollen and you can't see it.
可能有點腫還看不出來
but
但是呢
Huayin reaction blessing is the whole body
花陰反應加持是全身的話
that's serious
那就很嚴重了
Because it means that you have a lot of fluid all over your body
因為就表示說你全身很多的液體
Will flow from the blood vessel into the adjacent soft tissue
會從血管裡面流入到旁邊的軟組織
what will happen at this time
這時候會怎麼樣
lower blood pressure
血壓會降低
Will go into shock and die
會休克就會死亡
So powerful flower shade reaction
所以厲害的花陰反應
it causes death from shock
它會造成休克死亡
The main reason is that the single use of blood vessel currency has increased
最主要就是因為血管幣的單用增加
Inflammation has two other characteristics:
那發炎還有兩個特徵就是
This is basically the separation from the cells
這基本上是跟細胞分明出來
a prostaglandin
一個前列腺素
Called Posagranding is related
叫做Posagranding是有相關的
what are the common factors
那哪些常見的因素
Will they have a negative reaction together?
會一起發陰反應呢
we generally know to say
我們一般都知道說
exotic organisms
外來的維生物
But it's easiest to have a negative reaction together
但是最容易一起發陰反應了
So viruses, bacteria,
所以病毒細菌、梅菌
All kinds of vitamins will
各式各樣維生物都會
But the yin reaction is not
但是發陰反應不是
Only foreign bacteria will react negatively together
只有外來的細菌會一起發陰反應
Substances in the body can also cause inflammation
身體裡面的物質也會造成發炎反應
For example, if your body is subjected to physical or
比如說你身體受到物理性或
or mechanical impact
或機械性的撞擊
tissue is injured
組織受傷了
after the injury
受傷之後呢
Our injured tissues and cells will
我們受傷的組織跟細胞會
generate some danger signals
產生一些危險的訊號
also stimulates an inflammatory response
也會刺激發炎反應
what about the other one
另外一個呢
your physical stuff
你身體性的東西
such as uric acid
比如說尿酸
We all have uric acid in our blood
我們血液裡面都有尿酸
it is part of our body
它是我們身體的部分
In theory, it should not produce an inflammatory reaction.
理論上它應該不會產生發炎反應啊
but
但是呢
When our uric acid concentration is high to
當我們的尿酸的濃度高到
after a degree
一個程度之後
it crystallizes
它會產生結晶
Crystallization for our body
結晶對我們身體來講
it violates the original
它就是違反了原來的
steady state
恆定狀態
because it exceeds the standard it should have
因為它超出它應該有的標準
so it starts from a
所以它從一個
After turning into a crystal?
變成一個結晶之後呢
our body knows
我們身體又知道說
The body is not normal
身體不正常了
so our bodily receptors recognize it
所以我們身體感受器會認識它
Then there is also an inflammatory reaction
然後也會產生發炎反應
So this is called
所以這種叫做
sterile inflammatory response
無菌性的發炎反應
So after the inflammatory reaction?
所以發炎反應之後呢
if it disappears soon
假使它很快就消失的話
then we won't have symptoms
那我們就不會有症狀
But if it continues to inflame
但是假使它繼續發炎的話
That of course can cause serious symptoms
那當然就會造成嚴重的症狀
that can cause more serious symptoms
那會造成比較嚴重的症狀
Generally everyone is familiar with
一般大家比較熟悉的
It's all kinds of viruses
就是各式各樣子的病毒
Or this East
或者說這個East
or say some plum fungus
或者說一些梅菌
their various bacteria
他們各式各樣的細菌
When infected, it causes an inflammatory reaction
都會感染的時候是造成發炎反應
So in this case
所以在這種情形之下
Assuming that the amount of bacteria is small
假使說菌量很少的時候
or when the amount of virus is low
或病毒的量很少的時候
or our body has antibodies
或我們身體有抗體
when able to control it
能夠控制它的時候
we'll still go to the left
我們就會還是走向左手邊的
Response to business
就生意反應
fever headache
發燒 頭痛
we pressed it down later
我們後來把它壓下來
Just organize the humiliation and you'll be fine.
組織羞辱就好了就沒事了
But the bigger challenge we feel is
但讓我們覺得比較大的挑戰是
so-called pathological inflammatory response
所謂的病理性的發炎反應
It's when the inflammatory response doesn't stop
就是當發炎反應它不停止
In the end the tissue will be injured
最後組織就會受傷
tissue injury
組織受傷
after the injury
受傷之後呢
it's not going to tinker
它不是走修補
It's called repairing.
所謂的修補就是啊
If my liver cells are damaged
我肝臟細胞壞掉的話
I use liver cells to supplement
我就用肝臟細胞來補
then no problem
那就沒問題
my skin cells
我皮膚細胞
When I get hurt, I replace it with skin cells
受傷我就換成皮膚細胞
pen cells to mend
上筆細胞來修補
What we least like to see is
我們最不喜歡看到的是
fibrosis
纖維化
fibrosis means
纖維化的意思是說
when we hurt
當我們受傷的時候
Our body has a cell
我們身體有一種細胞
fibroblast
叫纖維細胞
called fibroblast
叫fibroblast
What about when you use it for repairs?
用它做修補的時候呢
it
它
will cause many problems
就會造成很多的問題
First
第一個
from the most superficial
從最表面的
You accidentally got scratched here with a knife
你這裡不小心被刀子劃了一下
Break down
破下
why break down
為什麼破下
because you patched it with
因為你修補著它是用
Fibroblast
纖維細胞
So a bar will be generated
所以就會產生一個巴
it's on the skin
那在皮膚上啊
there is a bar
有一個巴
Never mind
就算了
girls may hate
女孩子可能討厭
but boys can be sexy
但是男生可能就很性感
a lot of bar
很多巴
but this thing
但是這個東西
If it happens to your liver
要是發生在你的肝臟
that's not sexy at all
那就一點都不性感
it's serious
它就很嚴重了
what is it called
它叫什麼
it's called cirrhosis
它就叫肝硬化
If the lungs are inflamed
那假使在肺部發炎
What about after pneumonia?
肺部發炎之後呢
Fibrosis of the lungs
肺部的纖維化
then pulmonary fibrosis
那就肺部的纖維化
What are the consequences of fibrosis?
那纖維化的後果是什麼
is the function is gone
就是功能不見了
so there is nothing you can do in your liver
所以你在肝臟就沒有辦法
carry out this metabolism
進行這個代謝作用
even as it gets hard
甚至因為它變得很硬
Then the blood doesn't pass easily
然後血液不容易通過
Then the pressure in the hepatic portal vein increases
然後肝門禁脈的壓力增加
easy to bleed
就容易可血
then in the lungs
然後在肺部
when you have fibrosis
你就要是有纖維化的時候
Then the lungs can't breathe
那肺部就沒有辦法呼吸
that's like a lot of vacuuming
那就像很多吸塵症
The family likes to go there
各位家人喜歡去那個
Like Jiufen
像九份啊
Jiufen used to use that old miner
九份以前還用那個老礦工
Did you see them playing chess?
你看他們在下棋有沒有
Bring oxygen because he plays chess
帶個氧氣就是因為他長棋
by some wet lika in this ore
受到這個礦石裡面的一些濕利卡
it causes an inflammatory response
它造成發炎反應
fibrosis
纖維化
So this is the most serious problem
所以這個是一個最嚴重的問題
So I use this example
所以我用這個例子
you can tell
你就可以知道說
this inflammatory reaction
這個發炎反應
our worst concern is to say
我們最擔心的就是說
he can't stop
他沒有辦法中止
Then besides saying
然後除了說
In addition to causing immediate shock
造成多立即的休克之外
even if you survive
即使你存活下來
You still have this fibrosis
你還會產生這個纖維化
So in the past SARS infected patients
所以在過去SARS感染的病人
even after some of it survives
即使有些它存活下來之後
it will have side effects
它都會有些後遺症
That is, its respiratory function will be reduced
就是它的呼吸功能會降低
Mostly caused by fibrosis
最主要就是用纖維化所造成
in causing all fibrosis
在造成所有纖維化裡面
or be able to transpose the reaction inside
或者是能夠換引反應裡面
the main one
最主要的一個
The most important factor is
最主要的因素就是
There is a class of protein
有一類的蛋白質
we call cytokines
我們叫做細胞激素
Cytokines are
細胞激素就是
when the cells of our body
當我們身體的細胞
especially our
尤其是我們的
water polo cell
水球細胞
Especially the protagonist we are going to talk about today
尤其是我們今天要講的主角
giant cells
巨式細胞
being received
在受到
after infection
感染之後
it gets a virus
它會受到病毒
direct stimulus
直接的刺激
cell it will
細胞它會
produce a variety of cytokines
產生各式各樣的細胞激素
Physiological functions of chemokines are basically good
化妓素基本上在生理的功能是好的
The first one, for example, this one is called exorcising prostitutes
第一個比如說這個叫做驅化妓素
Wait a minute, I will zoom in and see if there is Chinese written
等一下我會放大視有寫中文的
It will attract a lot of cotton-padded cells
它就會吸引很多的棉衣細胞過來
carry out an inflammatory response
進行發炎反應
But it also contributes to the so-called self-inflicted
但是它也會促成所謂的本身造成叫做
The one that more strongly contributes to the increase of repairing diseases is called
比較厲害促成修管病增加的這個叫做
Inflammatory prostaglandin This is called Proinfotour Satellite
發炎妓素這個叫Proinfotour Satellite
Of course it also produces interferon
那當然它也會產生叫干擾素
That interferon is basically good
那干擾素基本上是好的
Because we all know that after interferon is produced
因為我們都知道干擾素產生之後
It inhibits the occurrence of viruses
它可以抑制病毒的發生
So this inflammatory reaction we both hate and love
所以這個發炎反應我們是又害又愛又恨
because you don't have an inflammatory response
因為你沒有發炎反應
you don't produce an interferon
你就不會產生一個干擾素
But what about when you have inflammation
但是呢當你發炎的時候
You will also have these bad for your health
你同時會產生這些對身體不好
Some cellular techniques that increase vascular permeability
會增加血管通透性增加的一些細胞技術
If a cell has a large amount of technology
那假使一個細胞技術量比較多的時候
It will cause a G
它就會造成一個叫G
cause damage to the organization
會造成組織的破壞
cause excessive inflammation
會造成發炎過度
In addition, I said that the swelling of the blood vessels
那另外就是我說血管的腫脹
inflationary increase
通脹性的增加
Then I will use an example below
那我下面用一個例子
you can tell
你就可以看得出來
You don't know if this is changed to a film
這個換成片你就不要清楚
When we usually have an inflammatory response
我們一般在發炎反應的時候
all go for a while
都去倒應照一時光
The patient is most afraid of seeing swelling
病人最怕就看到腫脹
so you see swelling
所以你會看到腫脹
and then reflect for a while
然後在倒應照一時光
Patients are most afraid of seeing this
病人最怕就看到這樣
a piece of white
白茫茫的一片
Said there was water in it
說裡面都有水
You probably know there's a lot of water in here
這大概都知道這裡面有很多水
Why
為什麼
Because when it's time to shine
因為在倒應照一時光的時候
high water density
水密度高
he can't penetrate
他沒有辦法穿透去
so if you see
所以假如你看到
There are many white things in it
裡面很多白白的
We knew there was a lot of liquid in here
我們就知道這裡面液體很多
How did that liquid come here?
那液體怎麼來了
now you understand
現在你們就懂
is an inflammatory reaction
就是發炎反應
This is typical in a SARS patient
這個是典型在一個SARS的病人
what happened
發生的情形
after being infected
就受到感染之後
Inflammation of the entire lung
整個肺部發炎
so when his whole lung
所以當他的整個肺部
when full of liquid
都充滿液體的時候
Of course the patient
當然這病人
he can't breathe
他就沒辦法呼吸了
we are going to put him
我們就要把他
sent to the interactive ward
送到交互病房裡面去
when it was listed
那在上市的時候
After the patient was sent to the interactive ward
這病人送到交互病房之後
everyone thinks
大家都覺得說
interactive ward can
交互病房可以
keep him alive
維持他的生命現象
Then the patient recovered
那這病人後來就好了
then please
那請問
how is the patient
病人怎麼好的
do our doctors have medicine
我們醫生有沒有藥
symptomatic treatment
那叫症狀治療
is also a treatment
也是一種治療
But there is no cure
不過也沒有特效藥
So the patient later
所以這病人後來
how good is he
他怎麼好的
or you should try to say
或者你應該去想說
So how do we treat this patient?
那我們怎麼去治療這種病人
Basically we have no cure
基本上我們是沒有特效藥
but what can a doctor do
但是醫生能夠做什麼事情
we give him a way
我們給他一種方法
supportive care
就是叫做支持性療法
That is to say
也就是說
He couldn't breathe
他本來沒有辦法換氣
So after we get to the interactive ward
所以我們到交互病房之後
we give him a high pressure
我們給他一個高壓
hyperbaric therapy
高壓高壓療
High ammonia oxygen because he is also under a lot of pressure
高胺氧因為他的壓力也大
He's high on oxygen and forced to pour it in.
他的氧氣高就強迫把它灌進去
Although there is water
雖然有水
I still put oxygen in
我還是把氧氣灌進去
Let his lungs still be able to give up
讓他這個肺部還是能夠放棄
So basically send it to the hospital
所以呢基本上送到醫院去裡面
Our most important thing is the sustainer of the phenomenon of life.
我們最主要這個叫做生命現象的維持人
supportive care
叫做支持性療法
Just let him go through this dangerous period
就是讓他度過這個危險期
So a lot of time to the hospital
所以很多到醫院的時候
They say it's dangerous
他們就說這個很危險
to go to the education ward
要到教育病房裡面
To bless him through the dangerous period
要保佑他能夠度過危險期
that's all
就這樣
well the problem is
好那問題是
After that dangerous period
那危險期完之後
he's fine, right?
他就好了對不對
the question is how good
問題是怎麼好的
We still have no medicine
我們還是沒有藥啊
just what
就是什麼好了
is our immune system
是我們免疫系統
Let him heal slowly
讓他自己慢慢修復的
i just said
我剛剛有講過
I said it in the first film
我第一張換成片就講過
The purpose of our entire inflammatory response
我們整個發炎反應的目的
not to kill the patient
不是要把病人殺掉的
The purpose of the immune response is to return to a steady state
免疫反應的目的是要回到恆定狀態
Just saying that sometimes the virus is too strong
只是說當有時候病毒太強
Or our body immunity is too weak
或者我們身體免疫力太弱
When the inflammatory response cannot be stopped
那發炎反應沒辦法中止的時候
He's going to cause a lot of inflammation
他才會造成很厲害的發炎
then cause death
然後會造成死亡
but once you get over that
但一旦你度過那個難關
when each system slowly
當每一系統慢慢起來
because we are infected
因為我們受到感染之後
we develop antibodies
我們會產生抗體
Our T cells activate
我們的T細胞會活化
So wait until our body
所以等到我們身體
after this difficult time
度過這個難關之後
We have time to let our body's T cells
我們有時間讓我們身體的T細胞
After slowly activating that antibody
讓那個抗體都慢慢活化之後
We can slowly suppress the virus
我們就可以能夠慢慢把病毒給壓制
avoid or die
避免就不會死亡
So a treatment like this
所以這樣子的一個治療方式
Let's think of a way
就讓我們想到一個方法
If there is an acute infection
假如是有一個急性的感染
Then there are 10,000 people in Taiwan
然後台灣有一萬人
or 100,000 people infected
或十萬人受到感染
when respirators are needed
都需要呼吸器的時候
what to do
怎麼辦
We're melting away so big
我們在融走那麼大
The melt away is sensitive to the virus
把融走受到病毒都感光
Inside the bed of the interactive virus
裡面的交互病毒的床
no more than 200 beds
不會超過兩百床
The whole of Taiwan adds up to about
全台灣加起來大概
I think there are probably thousands of beds at most
我看大概頂多上千床
One or two thousand beds would be great
一兩千床就了不起了
then we have so many people
那我們有那麼多的人
How to deal with infection
感染怎麼辦
So this gave me an idea at the time
所以這當時就給我一個想法
That is, do we have a way?
就是我們到底有沒有一個辦法
to be aware of this
去意識這種
pronunciation response
發音反應
then let it tide over
然後讓它度過難關
What about after the hard times?
那度過難關之後呢
it doesn't have to be in the aftercare ward
它不一定要到交後病房
As long as we have a miracle drug
只要是我們有一個神藥
type in
打進去
Then its pronunciation response is
那它的發音反應就
suppressed to the point where we can accept
受到抑制 控制到我們可以接受
won't make our range
還不會使我們的範圍
Then gradually the patient will
那慢慢的這病人它就會
recover that's fine
恢復 那就好了
it was a dream
這是當時的一個夢想
Okay, so what about the cytokine storm?
好 所以細胞激素風暴呢
basically
基本上呢
it is the cause of death
它是造成死亡的原因
then we today
那我們今天
Although SARS passed
雖然SARS過去之後
we are still very heavy on it
我們對它還是非常的重
Because of
是因為
There are many new viruses
還有很多的新的病毒
For example, after the end of SARS
比如說這個SARS完之後
It can still be called MERS now
現在還可以叫MERS
the other one is me
那另外一個是我
As you all know, there was a virus called H5N1 in Hong Kong a few years ago
大家知道 前幾年在香港有一個叫H5N1
this is the flu
這是情流感
Or last year there was a Taiwanese H7N9
或者說去年還有一個台商H7N9
when they get this infection
他們受到這個感染的時候
same as lungs
一樣都是肺部
symptoms like this
都會產生類似這個症狀
what about other than that
那除此之外呢
There is a class of viruses called that cause this
有一類病毒叫做會造成這個
So-called
所謂的
Virus of conjunctivitis
初血熱的病毒
we probably don't know
我們大概不要知道就是
In Africa there is a man called Ebola
在非洲有一個叫伊波拉
after he got infected
他感染之後
will be a great one
也會厲害的一個
first blood course
產生初血性的修課
The other one is in Taiwan
另外一個在台灣呢
We will have a slightly degraded virus
我們會一個比較輕微貶的病毒
Our name is Denge virus
我們叫登閣病毒
Denge virus?
登閣病毒呢
in general patients
在一般的病人
He developed a fever with some symptoms
他就產生一些症狀的發燒
He doesn't necessarily cause serious symptoms.
他不見得會造成很厲害的症狀
but in some people
但是在某些人
or in the elderly
或在年紀大的老人
after he was infected
他受到感染之後
he will cause class syndrome
他會造成修課症候群
basically like
基本上都是類似
It's all because he has too much cytokines
都是因為他的細胞激素太多
Bacteria will
細菌也會
So we're thinking
所以我們就在想說
In the end cytokine storm
到底細胞激素的風暴
what is his molecular basis
他的分子基轉是什麼
How on earth did he overcome this problem
他到底怎麼去克服這個問題
So I take this picture again
所以我再把這張圖
take it out again
再拿出來看
just found out
就發現說
why in the past
那在過去為什麼
Many immunosuppressive drugs have
很多的抑制免疫藥物都有
Then why can't this disease be cured?
那為什麼這個病會治不好
Okay, so what's the basic reason?
好 那基本上原因呢
Let me emphasize it again
我再把它強調一下就是
The cytokines we produce can be divided into three categories
我們產生的細胞激素可以分三類
The first one is called heparin
第一個是叫肝腦素
What about heparin, it inhibits virus replication
這肝腦素呢 它是抑制病毒複製
that is good
這是好的
But we pronounce the reaction
但我們發音反應啊
At the same time, the so-called trigger inflammatory hormone is produced
同時會產生那個所謂觸發炎激素
It will increase the permeability of the vascular bottle
它會讓血管瓶通性增加
it produces kimo liver
它會產生KIMO肝
Slightly degassing hormones so that the pronunciation is more responsive
稍微去化激素 這樣更加發音反應
so our problem
所以我們問題啊
When we were in SARS
我們在SARS的時候
I have thought of many ways
曾經想很多種方法
For example, someone said
比如說啊 有人說
Let's get on steroids
我們就打個類固醇好了
Steroids down to suppress its immune system
類固醇打下去 把它免疫系統壓抑
hyperphonic response
就可以避免過度發音反應
is this good
這好不好
not good what is the reason
不好 原因是什麼
that's because
就是因為
When the steroids go down
類固醇下去的時候啊
all suppressed
全部都壓抑制
You suppress the good and the bad, all of it
你把好壞部分 全部都把它壓下來
then we all know
那我們都知道
Moderate articulation response is required
適度的發音反應是需要的
So using steroids is different
所以用類固醇是不同的
that some people say
那有些人說
Now there is a class of
現在有一類的
There is a very powerful
有一種很厲害的
The head of the game is called TNF
賽頭看叫做TNF
can we suppress it
我們把它抑制住可不可以
Basically it doesn't work too well because the
基本上效果也不好 原因是因為
When the cell gas storm is generated
它細胞氣素風暴產生的時候
There are probably dozens of cytokines
那個細胞氣素大概有好幾十種
You can't just suppress one
你光是抑制一種也不行
So what is the best way
所以最好的方法是怎麼樣
the best way is
最好的方法就是
you have a way
你有一種方法
You only selectively suppress
你只選擇性的抑制
You keep this interferon going
你維持這個干擾素運作
But you only put these trigger meta bases
但是你只把這些觸發元基數
hold it back
把它抑制住
then you separate the two
那你把這兩個分開
Then it may be possible to achieve
那這樣子就可能可以達到
The effect of our treatment
我們這個治療的效果
So the biggest challenge is
所以這最大的挑戰就是
How to suppress only the trigger metafactor
如何只要抑制觸發元因子
and compartmentalization factor
及區化因子
then avoid inhibiting interferon
然後避免抑制干擾素
So when the idea came up
所以提出這個想法的時候
people say
人家就說
you want to dream, right?
你要做夢對不對
The problem is this
這個問題是這樣
We are the most beautiful dreams
我們就是有夢最美
Only with dreams can you have some imagination
有夢你才會有一些想像力
See if you can help me solve this problem
看有沒有幫你解決這個問題
the problem with this
那這個的問題
question when i put it
問題當我提出來的時候
many people are interested
很多人都很感興趣
because now the whole world has
是因為現在全世界有
There are a lot of new infectious diseases
有非常多的新型傳染病
almost all diseases
幾乎都造成的疾病
It's all related to Cell Storm
都是跟細胞風暴有關係
SARS, MERS, H5N1, common virus
SARS、MERS、H5N1、常病毒
I just talked about EBOLA
EBOLA這個我剛剛有講過
it's all a problem
這個都是一個問題
So as long as it can solve this problem
所以只要是能夠解決這個問題
It's not just about treating a virus
它不只是治療一個病毒
It can treat many viruses
它可以治療非常多病毒
resulting disease
產生的疾病
good
好
So when I think about it next time
所以接下來我就想清楚的時候
start experimenting
就開始要做實驗
Just say that SARS is so serious
就說這個SARS這麼嚴重
So we applied for the National Science Program
所以我們申請了國科學計畫
Then what
然後呢
finally
好不容易
The previous opportunity has come
前一下的機會都來了
SARS is gone
SARS已經沒了
So when doing this research
所以在當時要做這個研究的時候
a little frustrated
有點點沮喪
don't want to be depressed
也不能想沮喪
I'm glad to say that SARS will be brought under control soon
又慶幸說SARS很快就受到控制
But the people who do the research are
但是做研究的人就是
When you think you haven't even started
你想還沒想要開始著手的時候
he is too late
他已經來不及了
So then we thought
所以當時我們就思考說
Let's find a comparison
我們就找一個比較
Another virus for research
另外一個病毒來做研究
yellow virus
就是黃子病毒
so prevent virus
所以防止病毒
There are English called Pravy Viruses
有英文叫做Pravy Viruses
that it contains a lot of viruses
那它包含非常多的病毒
Including dengue virus is water to prevent viruses
包括登革病毒是水防止病毒
Japanese old source virus is also to prevent virus
日本老源病毒也是防止病毒
And more common in the West
還有在西方比較常見
A Cinnirohe virus called Wesnile
一個Cinnirohe的病毒叫Wesnile
There is also a recent very popular
還有最近一個很熱門的
The virus that was very popular last year was called the Zika virus
去年很熱門的病毒叫Zika病毒
It's all Pravy Viruses
它都是屬於Pravy Viruses
That's inside the dengue virus inside
那在這裡面的登革病毒裡面
There are probably all over the world
其中大概有全世界有
390 charming
390個迷人
That's 390 million people
就是有3億9千萬的人
are threatened by dengue fever approximately every year
大概每年都會受到登革熱的威脅
Then 96 charming
然後96個迷人
a more serious symptom
會產生比較嚴重的一個症狀
country where it happens
它發生的國家
in warmer countries
都是在比較溫暖的國家
For example in this
比如說在這個
throughout the
在整個的
Very serious in India
在印度的地區非常嚴重
And Southeast Asia
還有東南亞的地區
And Central and South America are very serious
還有中南美洲非常嚴重
then it is
那它在
it again causes a lot of real
它又會引起真正的很多
some cause encephalitis
有些會造成腦炎
Everyone knows it's Japanese encephalitis.
大家都很知道就是日本腦炎
Z card causes microcephaly encephalitis
Z卡又造成小頭症腦炎
But what we are more afraid of is the dengue graduates
但是我們比較怕的是登革出學的
Those who graduated from dengue
那登革出學的
Because dengue virus has four types
因為登革病毒它有四型
So now there is no good vaccine
所以現在又沒有很好的一個疫苗
The vaccine made in the Philippines a few days ago
那前些日子在菲律賓做的疫苗
not very successful
又不大成功
And it makes the patient worse
而且反而讓病人更嚴重
so we're trying to say yes
所以我們在想說好
then we use dengue virus
那我們就用登革病毒
study as an example
當個例子來研究
How does dengue virus cause cellular agent transfer
登革病毒的造成細胞劑轉是怎麼樣
After dengue virus infection
那登革病毒感染之後
It's basically inspired by Egyptian brindle
它基本上是受到埃及斑紋
this infected
這個所傳染的
then it compares
那它比較
Its special symptom is
它一個特別的症狀就是
when it is infected
它感染的時候
it all flares up and breaks out
它全都會發火 會發疹
platelets then drop
然後血小板會下降
The other body will be very painful
那另外一個全身會非常的疼痛
That's when it's more powerful when you go out of school
那在比較厲害的出學的時候
This is the tendency to go out of school
這是趨性的出學
It was found that the platelets decreased
就發現這個血小板下降
then this place
然後這個地方
if you have some injuries
假設你有一些受傷的話
the whole of this
整個這個
Running away after studying medicine is very scary
學醫就跑出來 非常可怕
What's more powerful are those children
那更厲害的是那些小孩子
Now when he has this inflammatory reaction all over his body
他現在產生全身的這個發炎反應的時候
wow he knew very humiliating reaction
哇 他就知道很羞辱的反應
The whole body is very red
那全身都非常紅
it's very scary
這非常可怕
Then there is no special medicine to treat it.
那這沒有什麼特別好的藥可以治療
So when we do this experiment
所以我們要做這個實驗的時候
how to think
怎麼去思考
how do we go about solving this problem
我們到底要如何去解決這個問題
that's like my first
那就像我剛剛第一張
The introduction to you is
所跟各位介紹就是
Our body wants to feel the inflammatory response
我們身體要感受到發炎反應
It must be because he has a lot of this receptor on his back
一定是因為他背很多這個感受器
detected
所偵測到
Then I drew these various shapes
那我畫了這些各式各樣子
these English names
這些英文的名字
It means that our organelles
就是表示說我們細胞器
There are various receptors
有各式各樣的感受器
on our blood oil
在我們血油上面
So I had an idea at the time and said
所以我當時就有一個想法說
This virus will be very harmful
這個病毒會很利害
cause an inflammatory response
引起發炎反應
will it be
會不會是
It stimulates these receptors on the cells
它是刺激細胞上面這些感受器
After stimulating these receptors
那刺激這些感受器之後
almost an inflammatory reaction
差一點點發炎反應
To be able to tell who, say, dengue virus or Ebola virus combined with
能夠知道說 登革病毒或是伊波拉病毒跟誰結合
Then I have a way to use a method to antibody or something
那我就有辦法用一個方法 才能抗體或什麼方式
suppress their irritation
把它抑制住他們的刺激
Then the whole pronunciation response can be reduced
那整個發音反應就可以下降
it's a very simple idea
這是一個非常簡單的想法
The idea is simple but it is difficult to implement
想法很簡單 但是呢 做起來很困難
What are we going to do in order to do this experiment?
我們為了要做這個實驗 我們要做什麼事情呢
We're going to get it from the blood bank. I was at Yang Ming University at the time.
我們要從血庫 我那時候還在陽明大學
That's the blood bank in Tamsui
那是血庫就在淡水
So my students often have to run into fresh water
所以我的學生就常常要跑到淡水裡面
to get a patient's blood
去取病人的血液
We just had some educational cooperation
我們剛才有一些建教合作
If you say you want to camp, use it
說要做營就使用
So with the patient's consent, we took some blood
所以經過病人同意之後 我們就取了一些血液
Blood cells are separated from the blood through a series of complex processes
從血液裡面就經過一連串複雜的方式分離血球
After the blood cell, we will store it
血球之後我們就存化
We only need to deposit a specific labeled C14 POS cell
我們只要存化一個特定標記的C14這種POS的細胞
It's MarcoForge for giant cells
它就是MarcoForge 就巨式細胞
Then we let it add cell technology
然後我們再讓它去加細胞技術
let it dedifferentiate
讓它去分化
What do you do after splitting up?
分化完之後做什麼事情呢
we start from
我們再從
We know that the cell
我們知道這種細胞上面
There must be many of these receptors
一定有很多這種感受器
So we use the techniques of molecular medicine
所以我們就利用分子醫學的技術
we'll go get the inside
我們就去把裡面的
RNA message
RNA的訊息
just translate it into cDNA
就把它翻傳成CDNA
then one by one
然後一個一個
Using a technique called PCR
用一個技術叫PCR的方式
to amplify these genes
去把這些基因放大
same as aquamarine
跟海底道症一樣
get it out one by one
一個一個把它弄出來
One is not enough after getting it out
一個弄出來之後還不夠
Because of this G you have to turn it into a protein
因為這個G你還要把它變成一個蛋白
So we're using the offensive
所以我們在利用進攻的方式
let's take it as an example
我們就當一個例子
this is a sensor
這個是個感受器
expressed in this cell
表現在這個細胞裡面
We need to know it is to extract its RNA first
我們要知道它就是先抽它的RNA
because we all know
因為我們都知道
Protein is converted from DNA to RNA
蛋白質是透過DNA變RNA
Change PoTin
變PoTin
so we pump it for RNA
所以我們抽它RNA
after flipping it out
把它翻轉出來之後
and then make it a cDNA
再把它做成一個CDNA
Then bind to this part of the antibody
然後再跟抗體的這一段結合
make it a fusion protein
把它做成一個融合蛋白
it will be easy
這將起來很容易
This is just to prepare these things yourself
這個光是自備這些東西
It took almost two years
就花將近兩年的時間
Then the experiment is easy to do
然後這個實驗做起來很容易
But it costs a lot of money to do it.
但是做這個還蠻花錢的
When doing this experiment
那當時要做這個實驗的時候
i'm lucky
我運氣很好剛好
At that time, it was sprayed on this Dean Weng Qihui
那時候有噴到這個翁起惠院長
Dean Weng said it was a good idea
翁院長就說這是很好的想法
worthy of encouragement
值得鼓勵
So you have to have this bullet in war
所以打仗都要有這個子彈
So he offered me some bullets
所以他就提供了我一些子彈
we spent two years
我們就花了兩年的時間
Just do this thing and do nothing
就專門在做這個事情什麼都不做
finally these weapons
終於把這些武器
Take these thirty or so proteins
把這個三十幾個蛋白
make it one by one
一個一個把它做出來
took a very long time
花了非常長的時間
when it's done
那做出來的時候
This is the most tense moment
這個就是最緊張的時刻
Is that idea right or wrong?
那想法到底對還是不對
I can't make it right, I'm thinking wrong, what should I do?
搞不好亂想是想錯怎麼辦
so it's tense
所以這很緊張
Of course we took two years to do it
當然我們把做花了兩年時間
It took a lot of time to support
花了很多支援的時候
After we made those Porting
我們做出那些Porting之後
Let's do a very intense experiment
我們就做一個非常緊張的實驗
So we just put this
所以就是我們就把這個
Each black represents a different protein
這每一個黑色就是代表不同的蛋白質
Of course not only that much
當然不只這麼多
it's a simple statement
這是一個簡單的說法
Just put dozens of proteins
就放了幾十個蛋白質
put it all on a plate
都把它放在一個盤子上面
Then put the virus on
然後再把病毒放上去
Then use antibodies to detect
然後再用抗體去偵測
is there any one
到底有沒有哪一個
made receptors
做出來的感受器
will combine with it
會跟它結合
So this experiment is actually pretty bad.
所以這個實驗其實蠻不好做的
Then one day when doing this kind of experiment
然後有一天做這種實驗的時候
Bosses are just as nervous as students
老闆也是跟學生一樣緊張
So we're in the lab
所以我們就在實驗室裡面
Then finally after several failures
然後終於經過了幾次失敗之後
One day my student came knocking on my door
有一天我那學生就來敲我的門
This Mr. Long is amazing after a long time
這個Long老師當久之後就厲害
Is the student doing well?
這學生結果好不好
don't ask
根本不用問
just look at him
就看他那個
Know the sound and frequency of knocking on the door
敲門的聲音跟頻率就知道
The one that knocks very slowly
那個敲很慢的
very listless
很沒有精神
Don't ask, it must be bad
不用問一定是不好
knocking fast
敲得很快的
must be a good result
一定是好結果
found it strange
就發現奇怪
This student knocked on the door before
這個學生以前敲門
that's not the sound knock
聲音不是這樣敲門
Knocking very briskly today
今天敲得特別輕快
probably good news
大概是好消息
I just invite him in
我就請他進來
Then he showed me this picture
然後他就拿這張圖給我看
He said he saw
他說好說看到
There are three receptors that bind to him
有三個受體會跟他結合
I am very happy to see this picture
我看這張圖非常高興
because the left-hand side of it is in two receptors
因為其中的左手邊在兩個受體
strong combination
結合很強的
this has been known in the past
這是在過去已經知道
He will combine with dengue virus
他會跟登革病毒結合
But he will only bond with him
但是他只會跟他結合
He's just responsible for his run into the cell
他只是負責他跑到細胞內
But he doesn't elicit the cell's response technology
但是他不會引起細胞的反應技術
what i see is this
我看到的是這個
It always looks different from the students
這就老是跟學生看起來不一樣
Students feel bad when they see this
學生看到這個都覺得不好
this combination is so low
這個結合這麼低
But after I saw this spirit
可是我當時看到這個精神之後
I'll look it up when I find it
發現我就去查這個精
what on earth do
到底做什麼
I just found this spirit very interesting
我就發現這個精神非常有興趣
because of this spirit
因為這個精神
that's what i saw
就是我看到這個
In the past biochemical experiments have been known to say
在過去生化實驗已經知道說
it sends a signal
它是會傳遞訊號的
Cell-Based
它下有可能會做細胞基礎
Didn't know so much at the time
當時還不知道這麼多
but i know there's a good chance this one
但是我知道這個是有一個很好的機會
So let's go ahead and study and say
所以我們就繼續來研究說
Is this receptor the same as we imagined
這個受體是不是就是我們之前的想像中
The virus stimulates receptors in its cell base
病毒會刺激它一起細胞基礎的受體
I was very nervous and started to do this experiment.
就很緊張就開始做這個實驗
Our experimental results are basically
我們的實驗結果基本上是
this is what we want
這是我們所要的
in a nutshell
簡而言之是這樣
what we see here
我們在這邊所看到
These English numbers TNF, RLA
這些英文數字TNF,RLA的
That's the name of the different cellular bases
這就是不同細胞基礎的名字
We found that once the virus is infected,
我們就發現病毒一感染之後
you find the black
你就發現這黑色的
After an infection
一感染之後
Although at different times
雖然在不同時間點
this is the hour
這是小時
You will find that this kind of odd number keeps going up.
你就發現這種奇數都一直上去
All kinds of odd numbers go up
各種奇數都上去
That was before we had antibodies
那當時我們還沒有抗體之前
We use a method called SRNA
我們用一個叫做SRNA的方式
It is to suppress the performance of this G
就是把這個G的表現抑制
You just put this 5A and this TC3
你就把這個5A跟這個TC3
hold it back
再把它抑制住
i just said
我剛剛講過
One of these three acceptances will catch the virus
這三個受理其中一個會抓到病毒的
This is the TC3
就是這個TC3
but it doesn't send a signal
但是它不會傳遞訊號
the other one
那另外一個
This is what we want to study the experimental group
這就是我們想要研究實驗組
you found out
你發現喔
When we take this 5A performance
當我們把這個5A的表現
when suppressed like this
這樣抑制的時候
It would have produced this CyroCAN
它本來會產生這個CyroCAN
just found it all down
就發現它都下降
decline
下降
wow very happy
哇 很高興
it all falls
它都下降
But this is not the point
但是這個還不是重點
if it all falls
它假如全部都下降
no discount again
又沒折了
how is it different from before
它跟以前有什麼不一樣
We're most excited to see this
我們最興奮的是看到這個
the one on the right
右手邊這個
This is Inferon
這個就是Inferon
interferon
就是干擾素
you found out
你發現喔
after you drop it
你把它弄掉之後
Well, interferon does not affect
欸 干擾素不影響
wow that day i probably
哇 那那天是我大概
After spending so much money on this
這個花了那麼多錢之後
the happiest day
這個最開心的一天
just do this experiment
就是做這個實驗
Probably just to show
大概就是顯示說啊
what we did
我們所做的這個
find this receptor
找到這個受體啊
It only controls its inflammatory response
它只控制它的發炎反應
production of sex hormones
性性激素的產生
But this receptor it doesn't control interferon
但是這個受體它不會控制干擾素
So this is a receptor for the meditative
所以這個就是悶想的一個受體
finally come true
終於成真這樣
then we were thinking
那我們就在想說
So is there any way to find this?
那找到這個到底有沒有方法
to prove that it really matters in the body
去證實說它在體內真的很重要
Then we need to prove the effect in the body
那要再證明在體內的作用
Of course basically we need an antibody
當然基本上我們是需要一個抗體
Because of the antibody everyone knows
因為抗體大家就知道
Antibodies can be used to treat many diseases
抗體可以用來治療很多的疾病
treatment-resistant cancer
抗治療癌症
There are also many people who are suitable for every subject
還有現在很多每一封適科的人
They are using Amber
他們在用安博
It's because you used to have a lot of pain from the sealed wet joints.
就是你本來以前對封濕性關節很痛
I used to be too pure
以前都整個弄類過純
Now take an antibody and it will be cured
現在打個抗體就把它治好了
So antibodies are a very important
所以抗體是一個很重要的
That antibody is basically in the body
那抗體基本上在體內
We all know that there are many antibodies
我們都知道有很多的抗體
Our body has many cells
我們身體有非常多的細胞
have a lot of antibodies
有非常多的抗體
so science in the past
所以科學在過去
they just know
他們就知道說
Suppose I produce an antibody today
假設我今天生產了一個抗體
After the antibody hits the body
在抗體打到體內之後
I follow my standard U
我就跟我的標的U
Like here it is marked with TNF
像這裡面它是用TNF做個標的
or cell wipe
或是細胞抹都可以
When a target antibody is knocked down
當一個標的 抗體打下去之後
it can cure it
它就可以把它治好
But antibodies, although they are so useful
但是抗體喔 雖然是這麼好用
But it's hard to make
但是它滿難製作
because our internal
因為我們在體內的
PC packs so much
PC包那麼多
Each PC bag produces different antibodies
每一個PC包產生抗體都不一樣
then you have a challenge
那你就有一個挑戰
If you take this particular PC bag out of your body
你如果在體內把這個特定的PC包拿出來
and find out that the antibody it made is exactly what we want
然後找出它做的抗體剛好是我們要的
and then be able to generate
然後又能夠帶上產生
This is a difficult
這個是一個高難度的
so we would like to thank you very much
所以我們就要非常感謝
an important technology
一個重要的技術
This is called fusion flow cell fusion flow
這個叫做融合流細胞融合流
That was discovered by three scientists
那這是由三位科學家所發現的
This is Drin
這個叫Drin
This Color and Mustain
這個Color 跟Mustain
They all got Norbert to talk
他們都得到Norbert講
Norbert speaking in 1980
1980年Norbert講
that they figured out a way
就是他們想出一個方法
Because our PC bag
因為我們這個PC包
Basically though it will do antibodies
基本上它雖然會做抗體
but the cells die
但是細胞都會死亡
What's the only way to keep it from dying?
那唯一讓它不死亡的方法是怎麼樣
turn it into a cancer cell
就把它變成癌細胞
cancer cells won't die
癌細胞就不會死
So inventing a fusion flow technology
所以在發明一個融合流技術
It combines this PC bag with cancer cells
它就把這個PC包跟癌症細胞把它合在
That's a really interesting idea
這實在是一個非常有興趣的想法
the cell will not die
這細胞就不會死了
won't die
不會死了
it's going into some complicated way to pick it out
它是在進入一些複雜的方式去把它挑出來
Pick out a B cell that has been making antibodies
挑出讓一個B細胞一直在做抗體
but won't die
但是又不會死亡
So we can disassemble and select from this different neutralization flow
所以我們就可以從這個不同的中和流裡面去拆選
we want antibodies
我們要抗體
We will use this technology to start making antibodies
我們就用這個技術開始再去製造抗體
So when my students hear the teacher say
所以當我的學生聽到老師說
When he is asked to go for antibody therapy again
要他再去做抗體治療的時候
I use students to color
我用學生點色
Instantly went from happy to depressed
馬上從那很高興的變得很沮喪
It's been so long
前面已經搞了那麼久了
more than two years
兩年多了
two or three years
兩三年了
and now make antibodies
然後現在做抗體
Teacher, tell me how long I will do it
老師你講一句我要做多久
So the student immediately the excitement
所以這個學生就馬上這個興奮之情
gone soon
馬上就不見了
Just go back and start working hard to make antibodies
就回去就開始努力做抗體
Then we disassemble and select the antibody we want
然後就拆選到我們要的抗體
Three years after the antibody came, it was another big day
那三年抗體來之後又是一個大日子
is it useful
到底有沒有用
So our student is basically
所以我們那個學生基本上就是
He took the five-digit antibody we wanted
他就把我們要的這個五位的抗體
Hit the rat alive and immunize him
打到老鼠生生把他做免疫
After immunization, he developed antibodies
免疫之後他就產生了抗體
After producing antibodies, he produced a lot of B cells
產生抗體之後他就產生了很多的B細胞
After the B cell, he fuses it with the swollen cell
B細胞之後他就跟這個腫的細胞把它融合
Then use a drug screen to screen
然後再用藥物一個篩選篩選
It's easy to say anyway
就反正講起來也很容易
It takes about a year to talk in one minute, and that's it.
一分鐘講完他大概做一年就這樣
So we worked for a long time and finally got several antibodies
所以我們就搞半天就終於得到好幾個抗體
What about when the antibody comes?
那這個抗體來的時候呢
We hit the rats
我們就打到老鼠生上
Then we use a mouse model
那我們用一個老鼠的模式
When the mouse basically hits in, you will find
這個老鼠基本上打進去的時候你會發現
he will bleed
他會出血
so put the mouse behind you see
所以把老鼠背後你看到
That's a lot of bleeding
這很厲害的出血的現象
The intestines are also bleeding
這腸子也出血的現象
Then we put our production of this antibody
那我們把我們生產這個抗體
This is the control antibody
這是控制組的抗體
Because doing time requires a control group
因為做時間都要一個控制組
This is an antibody with no specificity
這個是沒有特異性的一個抗體
it is not protective
它是沒有保護效果
This is one of our antibodies
這是我們其中一個抗體
You'll find typing this
你會發現打下去這個
His subcutaneous bleeding has been suppressed.
他皮下出血都做到抑制了
Intestinal bleeding was also suppressed
腸子出血也都受到抑制了
What about re-entry proof?
那為了再進入證明呢
we'll just do a dye
我們就打一個染劑
That's called Even Blue
那個叫做Even Blue
Because of this blue dye
因為這個藍色的染劑
It usually does not increase in vascular access
它平常血管通路性不增加的時候
it's inside a blood vessel
它是在血管內
But once the pronunciation reacts
但一旦發音反應之後
Its vascular access is increased
它的血管通路性就增加
After the increase, it will run outside and go out
增加之後它就會跑到外面出去
So you start from the shade of its color
所以你就從它那個顏色的深淺
you can tell
你就可以判別說
changes in its vascular access
它血管通路性的變化
Is it suppressed
到底有沒有受到抑制
This is an easy experiment to do
這是一個很容易做的實驗
recently discovered
最近發現啊
This is the antibody of the control group
這個打控制組的抗體
or do not fight are blue blue
或不打的都是藍藍的
After the antibody, you will find that it is not blue anymore
抗體之後你會發現說它又不藍了
Then in this liver
然後在這個肝臟啊
Basically processing is inhibited in the gastrointestinal tract
在腸胃道基本上處理都受到抑制
OK, what about after the fight?
好 那打完之後呢
Review was not satisfied when this submission was made
這個投稿的時候Review還不滿意
He said, are your antibodies so good?
他說那你們抗體那麼好嗎
Just like the Amber we just talked about
你就跟我們剛剛講的那安博
bad food diet
就是為抑制種的壞食飲食
that drug to compare
那個藥物來比較
This antibody sells about 10 B chains a year
這個抗體一年大概賣10個B鏈
There are 10 B chains in the world
全世界有10個B鏈
U.S. dollars are 10 billion U.S. dollars
美金 就是100億美金
This is a very big medicine
這個是非常大的一個藥
Let's compare and see if its blue rendering is suppressed
來比 然後就看它這個藍色的呈現度有沒有受到抑制
Then you are on the right hand side with this green is under control
那你在右手邊跟這個綠色是控制住
You just find out and say wow it's infected and it's very blue
你就發現說 哇 它是感染之後它就非常的藍
Then we hit the antibody, the ambo, the ambo
然後我們打了抗體 打了這ambo這ambo
There is some effect, but it is not very obvious, just purple
有一些效果 但是也不是很明顯 就紫色的
But after taking our antibody, you will find
但是打了我們這抗體之後你會發現
It's red to see it's all suppressed
就是紅色的看到 它都受到壓制
So from this quantitative experiment you can clearly
所以由這個定量的實驗 你就可以很清楚的
It can be known that if the antibody is knocked down, it can indeed kill it.
可以知道說這抗體打下去確實是可以把它的
Vascular permeability Inhibited
血管通透性 抑制住的
Then let's look at its survival rate
然後我們再去看它的存活率
This is an early experiment, after doing this experiment
這是早期的一個實驗 做這個實驗之後
You find that no treatment or control treatment
你就發現 沒有治療或控制組治療
The rats all died within two weeks
這個老鼠在兩個禮拜全部都死亡
But we hit one of the antibodies
但是我們打了抗體裡面其中一個抗體
Works well, about 50% of the mice don't die.
效果不錯 大概有50%的老鼠就不會死亡
So doing this experiment is finally a success
所以做到這個實驗終於炸弓告成
My student finally said, teacher, are you satisfied now?
我的學生終於說 老師這下子你滿意吧
I can graduate, okay?
我可以畢業了吧 好
Not yet, why, because I haven't cheated yet
還不行啊 為什麼 因為還沒有偷搞
So we later wanted to say that this study was good.
所以呢 我們後來就想說 這個研究不錯
Let's go and submit to a journal called Nature
我們就去投到一個雜誌 叫做自然雜誌
This nature journal is considered to be currently in the Holy Literature
這個自然雜誌呢 算是目前在聖文學
It's a top-notch magazine, so let's try it out.
算是一個頂尖的雜誌 我們就試試看
After they voted in, they thought our stuff was very interesting.
那投下去之後 他們就覺得我們東西很有趣
so quickly accepted
所以很快就接受了
after accepting
接受之後呢
Let's make a picture like this
這個 我們就做一個這樣的一個圖
Let's summarise what we found
來 summarise 我們所發現
That was basically in 2008
那基本上就是在08年的時候
We will submit to this research journal
我們就投到這個研究雜誌
You just draw a picture to explain the concept
你就畫張圖來解釋這個觀念
Which means we found something in mice
就是說 我們在老鼠身上有發現
normal infection time
一般的感染時候
you will generate a lot of this
你會產生很多這種
The so-called Trigger Addiction Base is on the left hand side.
所謂的觸發癮基礎 在左手邊
Then you increase the permeability of Chen Qius tube
然後你就照陳秋管性的通透性增加
After the permeability is increased, the mice will eventually die.
通透性增加之後呢 最後老鼠會死亡
After we fight this resistance, it basically suppresses the virus
我們打這個抗理之後 基本上它就抑制病毒
it stimulates this receptor
它刺激這個受體
So it's still a bit of a fix it's already reacting
所以呢 它還是有點修復它已經反應
But this amount is not high
但是這個量不高
But the hepatic derivative is not affected
但是呢 這個肝導數是沒有受到影響的
so it's blood vessel angiovirus
所以它血管的 血管病毒
So in this way, we proved that the last immunity of this mouse
所以這樣子這個老鼠後來他最後的免疫力我們證明
Although this mouse received treatment
這個老鼠雖然接受治療之後
He will eventually develop antibodies
他最後還是會產生抗體
His Tc activation does not affect the subsequent immune response at all
他Tc化的活化完全不影響到後續的免疫反應
So the mouse will survive
所以這個老鼠就能夠存活
so this is our job
所以這個就是我們的工作
Then another interesting thing happened when this was submitted
然後這個在投稿的時候又發生了一個有趣的事情
when we were submitting
就是我們在投稿的時候
Basically, this magazine has a bit of news
基本上這個雜誌都有一點新聞性
So he always said that it is not allowed to publish without our permission
所以他都說未經我們允許不准發表
Because you retracted your paper after you published it
因為你發表之後你就把你撤稿
Wow everyone is serious
哇 大家就很嚴重
After working for so long, the manuscript was withdrawn next to each other
工作那麼久就被撤稿挨著了
the result is very tense
結果就很緊張
But one day I got a call
可是有一天我接受到一個電話
just say i'm a so and so newspaper
就說我是某某報紙
The British newspaper said that I want to interview you
英國的報紙說我要訪問你這個事情
I was shocked when I heard that, and I said how do you know
我聽了嚇了一跳我說你怎麼知道
I said I can't tell you
我說我不能跟你講
What should I do if my manuscript is withdrawn after I told you?
我跟妳講之後被撤稿怎麼辦
He said it doesn't matter, we are going to advertise for you
他說沒有關係啊我們是要幫你做廣告的
so i just
所以我就
I'll tell him a little later
後來我就稍微跟他透露一下
I didn't expect that he really advertised for me.
結果沒想到他真的是幫我做廣告
he advertises
他就做廣告
this ad
這廣告啊
not too small
還不小
call me that
那個找電話給我
it's a british newspaper
就是英國的報紙
called Telegram
叫做Telegram
He helped us board a
他就幫我們登了一個
a discovery
一個發現
say this
說這個
A Breakthrough
一個Breakthrough
doing dengue treatment
在做登革的治療
Is Breakthrough
是Breakthrough
so here's his report
所以這是他的報道
Ah, is this English?
啊這英文嗎
of course i understand
我當然看得懂
Can you understand this?
這個你看得懂嗎
this he can see berlin
這個他看得到柏林
take a look here
這看一下
more like german newspapers
比較像德國的報紙
Then how do I know he reported me?
那我怎麼知道他報我呢
Because only dengue
因為只看到登革了
He sees series 5A
他看到系列5A
i was thinking
我在想說
This should be reporting something to me
這應該是在報告我的東西
So which of my classmates see
所以我哪個同學看
he said nothing wrong
他說沒有錯
this is reporting your news
這是在報道你的新聞
this is a german newspaper
這是德文的報紙
this is AFP
這是法新社
of course
這當然
we understand
我們看得懂
Do you guys understand?
這各位看得懂嗎
what text is this
這什麼文
It is said that this is a bilingual
據說這是二文
I also can not understand
我也看不懂
But all I see is this
但是我只看到這個
I'll come back to know that I'm reporting our news
我再來知道說在報我們的消息
probably not wrong
大概是沒有錯
So Russian newspapers report
所以俄國的報紙報導
People's Daily
人民日報
Eating our tofu is said to be a Taiwanese scientist
吃我們豆腐說是台灣科學家
OK People's Daily also reported
OK 人民日報也報導
Then what is this text
然後呢 這個是什麼文
This seems to be from Central and South America
這個是好像是中南美洲的
basically like spanish
基本上好像是西班牙文
basically the same report
基本上也是做同樣的報導
and this
還有這個呢
This doesn't seem to be the case
這個好像不是這樣
It is said that it seems to be Thai
據說這是好像是泰文
I don't understand the same
那這個一樣我看不懂
But I just look at the keywords
但是我就看關鍵字
this dengue fever
這個登革熱
Sidereal look
Sidereal看
Nature No A
Nature 無A
I'm probably saying I'm probably not wrong
大概在講我大概沒有錯了
Finally, it seems to be in Vietnamese
最後再來好像是越南文的樣子
also do the same thing
也是有做同樣的一個事情
so what
所以呢
basically this is a story
基本上這個是一個故事
that is one of us
就是說我們一個
from a very simple idea
從一個很簡單的想法
just one stimulated by reflection
就一個受到反省刺激
then we start
然後呢 我們開始
Let's think about it, after thinking about it
我們去思索 思索之後呢
Let's think about someone from the past
我們去想一個以前人
a question never thought of
從來沒有想過的一個問題
then we get rid of it
那我們把它解決掉
later
後來
So this is one that makes us feel
所以這個是一個讓我們覺得
Doing scientific research this is probably
做科學研究這個大概是
feel most encouraged
感到最有鼓勵的
It means you have an idea in Chinese
就是說你一個想法中語呢
You are not bored come true you bored wish come true
你在沒悶成真 你也悶想成真
prove what you think
證明你的想法是這樣
Well, after we have that experiment
好 那我們有那個實驗之後
Next I'm going to add a little more
接下來我要再稍微補充一下
People will say you're just treating dengue fever
人家會說 你這只是對登革熱
there are so many viruses
那還有那麼多病毒
what's the use
那有什麼用
Are you real?
你這個到底是不是真的
So then we're at Yellow Paper Virus
所以後來我們在黃紙病毒呢
We also made two viruses
我們也做了兩個病毒
A virus that makes Japanese old people
一個做日本老人的病毒
Basically also get similar results
基本上也得到類似的結果
Then we also make a New Nile virus
那我們也做一個新尼羅的病毒
did a basically similar result
做了一個基本上類似的結果
after that
做完之後呢
Another problem is
另外一個問題就是
need some imagination
要一些想像力
Is it really only effective against dengue virus
它真的只對登革病毒有效嗎
Does it have a similar effect on other viruses?
對其他病毒有沒有類似的效果
then i have a good partner
那我有一個很好的夥伴
It's Dr. Yan Huilin at the University of Hong Kong
是閻惠琳博士 他在香港大學
Because of Hong Kong's love flu, they are doing this special movie Fu En Za
因為香港有情流感 所以他們專門在做這個影福恩雜
Yingfu Enza This influenza virus is harmful to humans
影福恩雜這個流感病毒他的對人類的危害性
Indecent to dengue virus
不雅於登革病毒
You see he is very complex, he has many types
你看他很複雜 他有很多型
He has H and N H has type 18 N has type 11
他有H跟N H有18型 N有11型
He is also a virus and then mutation
他本身也是昂而病毒 然後會mutation
After his mutation changes, many of his drugs are of course ineffective
他mutation變來變去之後 很多他的藥物當然就沒有效
So we were thinking
所以我們當時在想說
We can use a similar concept for such virus blessing
這樣的病毒加持我們可以用類似的概念
Wouldn't it work for us to suppress his vocal response?
我們去抑制他的發音反應是不是有效
So we picked that H5N1 to do
所以我們就挑了那個H5N1來做
His danger to humans you can see from this table
他對人類的危害 你可以從這個表格看得到
During the two years from 1989 to 1990
在1989年到1990年 這兩年時間
When H2N2 infected this Russian food
H2N2在這個Russian food感染的時候
1 million deaths
100萬人死亡
The most famous one from 1988 to 1999 is the H1N1
最有名的這個1988到1999年 這H1N1
The most serious death in history is about 50 to 100 million
這個歷史上最嚴重大概50到100個 million 的死亡
this is a very scary number
這是非常可怕的數字
Also in the early 20th century
也是在20世紀的初期
about 100 years ago
大概100年前
Are we 2018 this year
我們今年是2018嘛
that 100 years ago
那100年前
it's scary
這很可怕耶
This million seven trillion yeah
這百萬七萬億耶
50 to 100 million deaths
五千萬到一億人死亡
that's an incredible number
這是不得了的數字
In another H1 virus
在另外一個H1的病毒
There are also about two million in H2N2
在H2N2大概也有兩個 million
Then Hong Kong is about a million
然後香港大概是一個 million
So now I'm probably scared
所以現在大概就很怕
in case there is one
那萬一有一個
What should I do if another very powerful virus comes out suddenly?
突然又來一個很厲害的病毒怎麼辦
That's why we did this experiment
這也是我們做這個實驗的原因
We'll get a genetically engineered virus
我們就拿到一個基因重組病毒
This is from the University of Hong Kong
這從香港大學來
It can be operated in P2S1 time
它可以在P2S1次操作
This is called H5N1
這個叫H5N1
That's the first thing we say
那一樣我們第一個就是說
Will it follow a lot
它到底會不會跟很多的
This Lectin combines
這個Lectin結合
Then we found out that it really
那我們就發現它果然
Can be combined with many Lectins
可以跟很多Lectin結合
one of them
其中一個呢
Obviously it is this C-Lectin that sends A
很明顯就是這個C-Lectin發 A
it will unite with it
它以示會跟它結合
So we'll use this grid
所以我們就用這個燈格
Use this H5N1 to see
用這個H5N1來看
Does blocking it work?
去阻斷它到底有沒有效果
So basically why do this thing is the same
那基本上為什麼要做這個事情也是一樣
Because although bird flu
因為雖然禽流感
Its infection is higher on this cell than
它的感染是在這個上比細胞
But its main bad flu
但是它最主要的差流感
It still comes from this MACOVAGE
它還是來自於這個MACOVAGE
So the same thing we think is to say
所以一樣我們想法是說
Although it cannot inhibit the infection of the virus
雖然它不能夠抑制病毒的感染
i was just about to say
我剛剛要講過
When I was doing dengue virus treatment in front of me
在我前面做登革病毒治療的時候
It has a characteristic that I forgot to mention specifically, that is
它有一個特點我忘了特別講就是
when we fight
我們這個打下去的時候
In fact, the virus has not decreased
其實病毒是沒有減少的
the virus is still inside
它病毒還是在裡面
But the virus is inside
但是病毒雖然在裡面
But it won't eat our RECEPT
但是它就不會吃激我們的RECEPT
So it was cleared in the end
所以它最後是被清掉
So we want to say yes
所以我們要想說好
Although this is not the same as dengue virus
雖然這個它跟登革病毒不一樣
Dengue virus can be found in
登革病毒是可以在
Dead cells grow a lot inside each other
去世細胞裡面互之生長很多
But H1Y is mainly in this aspect compared with cell
但是H1Y最主要是在這個上比細胞
But it's going to make a bad flu or here
但是它要產生差流感還是在這裡
Then let's take a look at our test class
那我們看說那我們這個測類
Is it still valid
是不是還是有效
The results proved to be effective
結果證明還是有效的
So that is to say
所以也就是說
in all the past worlds
在過去所有的世界
in the experiment
在實驗裡面
Whether in dengue virus or
不管在登革病毒也好
Or it's the same if you're emotionally ill
或是在情有感病的都是一樣
we are without treatment
我們在沒有治療的狀況之下
Our cells are hyperactive
我們這細胞受到極度的活化
It generates a lot of this trigger source technology
它產生很多這種觸發源的技術
Then it will die is what I just said at the beginning
那它會死亡就是我剛剛一開始講的
It will increase the pain of this blood vessel
它會讓這個血管痛痛的增加
will focus on shock
會重點休克
Will be quadriplegic
會四肢麻痺
then die
然後會死亡
So if we have a good antibody
那假如我們有一個好的抗體存在的時候
What about after this antibody blocks it?
這個抗體去阻斷它之後呢
Basically it is possible to make it this amount
基本上它是可以讓它的這個量
After this antibody is knocked down
這個抗體打下去之後
Antibody against five
這對付五位的抗體
It makes this inflammatory technique so less
它就讓這個發炎技術這樣減少
But its infectious agent still exists
但是它的感染素還存在
what is the benefit
那這個好處是怎麼樣
We are all
我們都是
What about viral replication?
病毒的複製呢
Many of our drugs are under control
我們現在很多的藥物都是在控制
replication of the virus
那個病毒的複製
But sometimes when it develops resistance
但是有時候它產生抗性的時候
you can't heal it copy
你就沒辦法醫治它複製
Our treatment is
我們這種治療方式是
Whether the management virus has mutated
管理病毒有沒有去突變
as long as you virus last
只要你病毒最後
It has to have limbs this
它都要經有四肢這個
If 5A is used to produce inflammatory hormones
就5A來產生發炎激素的話
I just block this part
我就只阻斷這一段
no matter what virus you are
不管你是什麼病毒
Assuming your virus doesn't stimulate 5A
假設你的病毒不會刺激5A
It certainly doesn't cause an inflammatory reaction
它當然就不會造成發炎反應
But the virus assumes it still wants
但這個病毒假設它還是要
If an inflammatory response occurs through this 5A
經由這5A產生發炎反應的話
I just need to block him
我就只要把他阻斷的時候
I can bring the inflammation down
我就可以把發炎帶來下降
Finally let the body
最後讓身體
his symptoms relieved
他症狀減輕
and then allow the patient to tide over
然後讓病人就能夠度過難關
so this is our whole
所以這是我們整個
A treatment for cytokine storm
一個治療細胞激素風暴的
a new concept
一個新的一個觀念
ok so in the end
好 所以最後就這樣
that is to say it is
就是說這是
Most of this work is done at Yangming
這個工作大部分在陽明做的
My favorite mountain climbing in Yangming
我當時在陽明最喜歡去爬山
The Guanyin Mountain I see every day
這每天看的這個觀音山
so this
所以這個
I watch this every day
每天看的這個
when doing experiments
做實驗的時候
when can't do it
當做不出來的時候
I like to climb mountains to see the scenery
最喜歡去爬山看看風景
calm yourself down
讓自己冷靜一下
Especially when the experiment doesn't go well
尤其當實驗做不順利的時候
Look at the mountain climbing is pretty good
看看爬山是蠻不錯的
So I suggest you come and go
所以建議各位來多去
go to church runner
去教會跑跑生
Finally, I would like to thank many people
那最後要感謝許多的人
Including my student Xu Cuiling in the center
包括在中央的我的學生徐璀玲啊
And this teacher Lin Yiling who looks like a lot
還有這個像很多的老師林奕玲
Especially Teacher Lin Yiling
尤其是林奕玲老師
He's the one who first called me dengue virus
他是最早叫我做登革病毒的人
He is the first humble person in Taiwan to do dengue virus
他是我們台灣最早做登革病毒的謙虛
He taught a lot about dengue virus
他教很多登革病毒的知識
So this is a very good cooperation between our two sides
所以我們兩邊這是一個非常好的一個合作
Then also thank our vice president, Vice President Lu, Vice President
然後也感謝我們副院長 陸副中副院長
And this Dean Wang at the beginning
還有這個汪院長在我們一開始
This Baihui superstar gave us a support
這個百會巨星的時候給我們的一個支持
Then my many experiments basically
那我很多的實驗基本上
It was also completed in Yangming and various
也是在陽明跟種種完成的
that last love flu virus
那最後的情流感的病毒
This was given by Dr. Yan Huining, University of Hong Kong
這是由香港大學 顏惠寧博士給的
And his boss is Paris
還有他的老闆叫Paris
Paris is a very famous professor
Paris是一個非常有名的教授
He just came to Taiwan
他剛好解隔來過台灣
He is the first to identify
他就是第一個鑑定
The scientist who monitored the SARS virus
這個監聽了SARS病毒的科學家
So we now have a
所以我們現在跟香港大學有一個
good cooperation
很好這個合作
Then use this to represent
那也用這張來代表說
In fact, doing a research requires countless
其實做一個研究需要無數的
In addition to countless financial and material support
除了無數的財力跟物力支持之外
We still need a lot of scientists
我們還需要很多的科學家
students work together
學生一起工作
Then there are actually a lot of discussions in the middle
然後中間其實還有很多的討論
because of the experiment
因為做實驗
Let's talk about it now
我們現在講起來很簡單
It's easy for us to look back now
我們現在往後看就很簡單
Just do 1 2 3 4
就1 2 3 4就要做出來
In fact, when you look forward
其實在你往前看的時候
is a lot of friction
是很多分擦入的
Then spray a lot of measures
然後噴了很多措施
So this needs a lot of good friends
所以這個都是需要很多好的朋友
good partner
好的夥伴
Only by working hard can one overcome
功能努力才能夠一的克服
To achieve what we are today
達到我們今天這個成果
then i think it's this
那我想就是這個
It is our best video
就是我們最彰化的影片
thank you
謝謝各位
Li Ming
李明
Well, we thank Professor Xie Shiliang
好 我們謝謝謝實良教授
very good speech
非常精采的演講
And share him with us
還有跟我們分享他
this
這個
this success story
這個成功的一個故事
Then we do know that in our
然後我們確實知道在我們的
we have this
我們對這個
Those who do scientific research are
做科學研究的都是
we have a very
我們有一個很
is Passion
就是Passion
But it is often a difficult process
但是也是常常需要經過一些艱苦的過程
Then there will be some results
然後才會有一些成果
These results, especially in the case of Professor Xie
這些成果尤其在謝教授這個情況下
In fact, the impact on society is huge
事實上是對社會的impact是很大的
This is the way to treat some diseases in the future
就是以後有這種方式可以來治療某一些疾病
For example, Denge is hot, other emotions are like this
比如說燈閣熱啊 其他情流感啊這樣子
We just have time now for people to ask questions
我們現在就是有時間讓大家來發問
To encourage everyone, so we have the magazine Scienceman
為了鼓勵大家 所以我們有科學人的雜誌
If you have any questions, we will
有發問的我們就
Think of this magazine as
可以把這個雜誌給當作
as the nature of this encouragement
當作這個鼓勵的性質
Now here's one who starts
那現在這邊有一位開始
That's it
Busini
Hello teacher, this is the second time I listen to the teacher's speech
老師你好 我是第二次聽老師演講
I am the dermatologist at Chang Gung Hospital
我是那個長庚醫院的皮膚科律醫師
The topic of the teacher's speech last time was EBV
上次老師演講的主題是EBV
Then this time the words are
那這次的話是
I am also still very interested in viral infection
我也還是很有興趣的病毒感染
Then I have a few questions to ask the teacher
那我幾個問題想要請問老師
is the first to say
就是第一個就是說
Because the Passo group is in
因為Passo群在
That is to say, on our ice bed
就是說我們冰床上面
That is, many Passo groups will cause
就是很多Passo群會造成
Satocon stone looks like this
Satocon stone這樣子
That's actually being a patient
那可是其實當病人
When a Satocon stone occurs
發生Satocon stone的時候
He's actually pretty consistent
他的表現其實很一致
that's hard to find that says
那很難就是找到說
Accurate Passo group to treat
確確的Passo群來治療
Just come is the Antifiral group
就是來就是Antifiral群
That is to say, the patient
就是說就病人
Usually this happens
通常遇到犯這種情況
It's just that we are just shooting birds
就是我們就是亂槍打鳥
all antibiotics
全部的抗生素
All antiviral drugs are like this
抗病毒藥全下這樣子
The first question I want to ask the teacher is
那想問老師第一個問題是說
Do we currently have some cruell
我們目前有沒有一些cruel
It is the Satocon stone that can be used
就是可以利用就是Satocon stone
The type of his Satocon
他的Satocon的type
or his proportions and performance
或者是他的比例跟表現
pushing his Passo group back and forth
來回推他的Passo群
what kind of infection
是哪一種感染
This is the first one
這是第一個
The second is that I want to ask the teacher to say
第二個是我想問一下老師說
Hit CLEC5A Antibody
打CLEC5A Antibody
Come to suppress the function of Information
來那個抑制Information的這個作用
when is better
在什麼時候比較好
is post infection
是感染後
Then it is also effective to fight before infection
然後還是感染前打也有效
It's been a long time
那打久了
Like because honestly there are a lot of viral infections
比如說因為老實說很多種病毒感染都有
Then we can't have only one infection in our lifetime
那我們一生不可能只遇到一種感染
So if we later treated it as a preventative medicine
那如果說我們後來把它當作是種預防性的藥
like the gram flu
像是克流感一樣
Will you call more times
會不會多打幾次
Then it didn't work like this
後來就沒有效果這樣子
The third question I want to know says
第三個問題是我想知道說
Because I'm doing enterovirus now
因為我現在在做腸病毒
Then I want to know that it is the part of the enterovirus
那想知道說就是腸病毒的部分
It is enterovirus, which is actually a part of TLR
就是腸病毒它其實也是TLR的一個
later a reaction
後來的一個反應
But the weird thing is that it happens in some places
可是比較奇怪的是它就發作在某些地方
It's the throat, the palms, the soles of the feet.
就是喉嚨手掌腳掌
Can the teacher give me some advice?
那老師可不可以給我一點意見
That is why it only looks like this in these places
就是說為什麼它只在這些地方這樣子
Is there any marker
是不是有什麼marker
I can look for this
我可以去找找看這樣子
Thanks
謝謝
The first question is to say
第一個問題就是說
Is there any way we can contract these symptoms from it
我們有沒有辦法從它感染的這些症狀
Made back to what kind of virus it is
製造回對它是什麼樣的病毒
In fact, this problem is a bit difficult
其實這個問題是有點困難
because
因為
you know our body
你知道我們身體
suppose today
假設今天
We have today that sequencing technology called automatic
我們今天有那個叫做自動的定序技術
Next Generation Sequencing Technology
下世代的定序技術
You know suppose to put a person
你知道假設把一個人
After all the DNA is extracted from the whole body
全身在DNA都抽出來了之後
Ask your body's DNA
請問你身體的DNA
It's the DNA in your 23-pair display body
就是你的23對那個展示體裡面的DNA
Approximately how much DNA is in your body
在你全身的DNA總量大概多少
Does this student have any idea
這同學有沒有概念
Weird question, isn't it?
很奇怪的問題對不對
Shouldn't knowledge be protected? Baidu is my DNA.
不是應該保護知識百度是我DNA嗎
You first look at how much of your own DNA is in your house
你先來看你自己的DNA在你房子是多少
According to scientists' estimates, only about 20%
根據科學家的估算大概只有20%
what does that mean
那什麼意思呢
80% of your body
你身體裡面有80%的
There are many microorganic
有很多的microorganic
exists in your body
存在你身體
you have no idea who he is
你根本不知道他是誰
He was with you all his life
他與生就跟你在一起
This is what we now use to sequence
這是我們現在用定序
So the answer to the question is to say
所以這個回答的問題就是說
when we have one
我們當有一個人
You come to pronounce the reaction especially in the hospital
你來發音反應尤其在醫院裡面
I often spray that called
常常有噴到那個叫做
ass earrings
屁股耳環那種
then have a fever
那就發燒
don't know anything
根本不知道什麼
now of course
現在當然
Of course we have some sequencing technology to know who
當然我們有一些定序技術可以知道是誰
but even if you want to know who he is
但是即使你要知道他是誰
It's a long way to do treatment with you
跟你做治療是很大的距離
That's why we do research
這也是我們做研究的原因
That is to say, what I just said
也就是說我剛剛有講到
Viruses that can cause severe cell-based viruses actually have a characteristic
會引起厲害的細胞基礎的病毒其實都有個特性
That is to say, he will stimulate MACOFIG
就是說他都會去刺激MACOFIG
He will stimulate MACOFIG
他就會去刺激MACOFIG
For example, let's talk about some slower viruses
比如說我們講一些比較慢的病毒
For example, your Baxinian virus
比如說你這個Baxinian病毒
Some lots of virus or hepatitis B virus
有些很多的病毒或B-型肝炎病毒
Will he cause a cytomegalo storm?
他會不會引起細胞氣素風暴
he won't do so much
他不會造成這麼厲害
So it will cause a cytogenetic storm
所以會引起細胞氣素風暴的
Almost all will stimulate MACOFIG
幾乎都是會刺激MACOFIG
despinocytes
就是去刺細胞
So you said how to treat
所以你說要怎麼去治療
This is also the purpose of our research
這也是我們研究的目的
We treat these 5A
我們治療這5A
This is the first time to prove our concept that
這是第一次來證明我們的概念說
Our MACOFIG is
我們這個MACOFIG是
There is a receptor on it
上面有一個receptor
will detect the virus and cause an inflammatory response
會偵測病毒然後造成的發炎反應
The problem is that playing 5A doesn't work either.
那問題就是那打5A也沒有效
Of course you can think about our receptors
你當然可以想一下我們受體
so many
那麼多
It is unnecessary to know all viruses
無謂不可能認識所有的病毒
you rely on this
這個你憑
Our general Kang Ben trial to participate in feel
我們一般的康奔審去參與覺得
Why do I have so many receptors to bless him so powerfully?
那加持他那麼厲害我幹嘛那麼多的受體
So it must not be all
所以一定不是全部的
So in fact, what we are studying now has been
所以其實我們現在在研究的已經
Not just researching upstream anymore
不只是研究上游了
We're now looking at the downstream messaging that says he
我們現在研究說他下游的訊息傳遞
His message is that he is going down
他的訊息傳遞他到底是往下
how is this passed down
這是怎麼往下傳的
Then we can find a common ground to do
然後我們可以找到一個共同點來做
a comment target
一個comment target
Basically, there are many of us now
那這裡面基本上在我們現在很多的這個
The pronunciation response is basically cox 2
發音反應基本上都是cox 2
we all heard one
大家都聽過一個
Conscious pronunciation response is the cox 2 inhibitor is basically like this
意識發音反應就是cox 2 inhibitor基本上就是這樣
Because he often passes through this cox 2 when he pronounces
因為他發音的時候很多都會經過這個cox 2
So this finds the target
所以這找到 target
So we're going to cure the cell tech storm now
所以我們現在要治療細胞技術風暴
We've gone from the earliest days of this
我們已經從最早期的這個
Upstream, let's find out slowly
上游我們慢慢去找說
he may have many receptors
他可能很多的受體
But he's going to have a vocal response at the end
但是他最後要產生發音反應
he will be one downstream
他下游會一個
consistent delivery of a message
一致的一個訊息的傳遞
So we're trying to find the signal for that message right now
所以我們現在在努力找那個訊息傳遞的訊號
then go terminate it
然後去終止它
In this way we can use a medicine
這樣子的話我們就可以用一個藥
like cox2
就像cox2
we do cox2 you will compare almost any reaction
我們這樣cox2你會比較幾乎任何反應
It won't hurt after you get it down
弄下去之後它就不會痛
Basically the principle is like this
基本上原理就這樣
We also hope that we can find such a target
我們也希望我們能夠找到一個這樣標的
After that, no matter what kind of virus
那以後不管是什麼樣的病毒
The cytokine storm everyone created
大家造成的細胞激素風暴
We can all use this in therapy
我們都可以用這樣放在治療
Then your third question is to grow virus 71
那你第三個問題就是長病毒71
I have done this too
這個我也有做過
long virus 71 it actually
長病毒71它其實
It does not affect the severe cytokine storm
它並不影響很厲害的細胞激素風暴
So basically this we also experimented with
所以基本上這個我們也做過實驗
it doesn't stimulate
它並不會去刺激
subcell
這個劇次細胞
It also does not create a cytokine storm
它也不會產生細胞激素風暴
So the specific symptoms it produces are due to
所以它會產生的特定的症狀是因為
What kind of cell does the virus want to enter?
病毒它要進到什麼樣的細胞
It depends on whether there are receptors on the cell
它要看這個細胞上面有沒有它的受體
its receptor is
它這個受體是
receptors that help it get into the cell
幫它進到細胞的受體
It is different from the receptors of gill translucency syndrome we talked about today
跟我們今天講的腮透看症的受體不一樣
So because your body has a specific receptor
所以因為你身體有一個特定的受體
So the virus will go to specific cells
所以這病毒就會跑到特定的細胞去
like hepatitis virus
就像肝炎病毒
he actually goes to the liver
他就實際上跑到肝臟
he won't go anywhere else
他就不會跑到其他地方去
So this type of treatment basically
所以這種治療的方式基本上
It will be different from the strategy we talked about today.
跟我們今天講的策略就要不一樣
So this scientific question is actually
所以這個科學的問題其實
There is no way to solve it with just one ability
沒有辦法光靠一個能力解決
so doing cell trends is my specialty
所以做細胞趨勢是我的專長
But you just mentioned longevity poison 71
但是你剛剛講到長命毒71
presumably have a different strategy
大概要有不同的策略
For example, the most common thing is that everyone is developing vaccines.
比如說最常見就是大家很在發展疫苗
For longevity poison, it is said that this clinical trial
對長命毒據說這個臨床試驗
seems to be ok
好像還可以
Report on road seems to be all right
在道路的報告好像可以
So this requires a different strategy to treat
所以這個需要有不同的策略來治療
But the example I am talking about today is the most important
但是我講的今天這個例子最主要
All are based on cell trend storm
都是以細胞趨勢風暴為主
thank you teacher
謝老師你好
I want to ask
我想問一下就是
Recently, it is often heard that pharmaceutical companies are developing
最近也常聽到藥廠在發展
Lantern fever vaccine
燈閣熱疫苗
It is because he has many similar blood types due to the dengue virus
就是因為他因為登革熱病毒有很多種類似血型型
But so it often happens that there is no way
但是所以常常會遇到就是沒辦法
All types can be protected
全部每一種型都可以保護
So the development is not so smooth
所以其實發展也沒有那麼順
Then I just want to listen to Mr. Xie's speech
那我只是想聽謝老師的演講
This 5A
這個5A的
The will seems to be quite effective and quite tangible.
意志好像還蠻有效果的 也蠻實物的
That
那
And there are antibodies
而且抗體也都有了
Is there any pharmaceutical company willing to go?
是不是有藥廠會願意去
to this direction
往這個方面
5A go
5A去
Are you developing this drug?
做研發這個藥物呢
Thanks
謝謝
dengue virus
登革病毒啊
just two questions
就兩個問題
one is the vaccine
一個就是疫苗
because vaccines do
因為疫苗確實
inside all vaccines
所有疫苗裡面
And every time I see manufacturers of dengue vaccines, I say you are very brave.
然後每次看到做登革疫苗的廠商都說你們非常勇敢
Just pick the hardest one in the world to do
就挑那個全世界最難的來做
because he has a different
因為他有不同的
four blood types
四個血型型
Then we all know that dengue virus infection has a special phenomenon called
那我們都知道登革病毒感染有一個特別的現象叫做
is the antibody
就是抗體
It is a phenomenon called AD
就是一個叫AD的現象
It's your antibody
就是你這個抗體
As long as you can only synthesize one type
只要是你只能夠綜合一型
But if it cannot be combined with other types
但是不能綜合其他型的話
that sometimes he is a disaster
那有時候他是一個災難
when it cannot neutralize other types
它不能中和其他型的時候
The presence of this antibody prevents the disease from becoming more serious
這個抗體的存在防衛這樣疾病更嚴重
So doing vaccines
所以在做疫苗
it's a big challenge
這是一個很大的挑戰
how do you promise to say
你如何保證說
Get vaccinated after entering alone
一個人進去之後打疫苗
He can produce antibodies
他都能夠產生抗體
protect everything
對事情都有保護
this is a big challenge
這個是一個很大的挑戰
So of course it shouldn't be difficult
所以做這當然是不要困難
so as to say
那至於說
Can it be used to treat diseases
它可不可以用來治療疾病
i just said
我剛剛有講過
when we published earlier
我們在早期發表的時候
In fact, we have authorized a manufacturer in Chinese
其實是我們中文有授權一個廠商
let's give us some more money
我們再給我們一些錢
Then do this experiment
然後去做這個實驗
but i just said
但是我剛剛有講過
when you go to therapy
當你去治療的時候
Antibodies are basically more expensive
抗體基本上它還是比較貴
The other is the time you talked about
另外一個就是你講的時間
Someone just asked me
剛剛有人問我說
when is it effective
哪時候打有效
all infectious diseases
所有的傳染疾病
like you eat the gram flu
就像你吃克流感一樣
The sooner you eat, the more effective
就是越早吃越有效
Does that have a preventive effect?
那有沒有預防作用
With your blessing
有 你加持
i never did
我不做過
Bless you before you get infected
加持你在沒有感染之前
After you get the antibody first
你就先打抗體之後
it fights again
它再去打
basically it will help
基本上它是會有幫助的
So who is going to buy this antibody
所以誰會去買這個抗體
I often say should
我常常講說應該
should be sold to the U.S. Department of Defense
應該賣給美國的國防部
The United States likes to send giants to fight all over the world
美國最喜歡送巨人到全世界打仗
So it's better to get up first and then go to war
所以最好就是先打起身再去打仗
he may be asymptomatic
他可能沒有症狀
But after all, it is more impractical
但是畢竟比較不實際
Most of the sick spots are because he's already infected
大部分的病點都是因為他已經感染了
he has symptoms
他有症狀來了
Then he started to take medicine
然後他才開始去吃藥
So in practice
所以在實務上來講
Although using antibodies to prove that we are infected
用抗體雖然證明我們感染
but you have to make a drug
但是你要做一個藥物
Antibodies are not optimal
抗體並不是最理想
Because your house is not playing very early
因為你家不是很早在打
Because after many viruses are infected
因為很多的病毒感染完之後
We know that when a virus enters the body it produces a disease called
我們知道病毒進入身體會產生一個叫
called Biremia
叫做Biremia
There is a virus all over the world
就是全世界都有病毒
But his experiment won't be very long
但是他實驗不會很長
he'll be gone in a few days
他過幾天他就不見了
so at this time
所以在這時候
He welcomes the reaction while it's in progress
他歡迎反應在進行的時候
we did experiments
我們做過實驗
Suppose we play very late
假設我們在很晚期打的時候
The later you beat him, the worse the effect will be.
越晚打他效果越不好
So now our new treatment target
所以其實現在我們新的治療標的
It's that we're studying his messaging.
就是我們在研究他的訊息傳遞
It just depends on which virus he drives.
就是看病毒他到底驅動那個
Which % tax is the messaging
訊息傳遞是哪一個%稅
We hope to use small molecule drugs
我們希望是用小分子的藥物
Able to be like Costool
能夠像Costool
Go to Tarkey those specific molecules
去Tarkey那些特定的分子
then come for treatment
然後來做治療
This is probably more realistic
這個大概會比較實際
This is what we are working on now
這是我們現在在努力的方向
JV
JV
X
X
hello chase
Chase 你好
i want to ask two questions
我想請問一下兩個問題
the first one is you
第一個就是你在
The lectures on knowledge and karma are mentioned above.
知識想業的演講災要上面有提到說
In the future, this receptor may be a
他未來可能這個受體是一個
One of the treatments for the red wolf
治療紅頒性狼藏的一個
A New Direction for Calibration
標定的新方向
can you explain it to us
那可以幫我們解釋一下嗎
The second is to say that in fact, in your recent
第二個就是說其實在你最近
It is on the Nature Combination
就是在Nature Combination上面
It is mentioned that
有提到說就是
This receptor-deficient keratin in the liver
這個受體缺陷的角素在肝臟
lead to more severe inflammation
會引發更嚴重的發炎現象
can you explain it to us
可以幫我們解釋一下嗎
The two questions you just asked are
你剛剛問的兩個問題都是
In our recent post that
在我們最近發表那個
In the Nature Communications article
在自然通訊那個文章上
What kind of function does this receptor have?
問到說這個受體他到底有什麼樣的功能
We found that this receptor basically
我們發現這個受體基本上
He not only knows about viruses
他不只會認識病毒
He will also know Seohyun
他還會認識細炫
Why do this research?
為什麼做這研究?
Because if you think about it, how can our body have a society to make it?
因為你去想我們身體怎麼會有一個社體做出來是
Made you sick
專門讓你生病了嘛
isn't that reasonable
這不大合理嘛
So it must have some other function
所以它一定有其他的功能存在
then we're in a place where we have a chance to find out that it's actually
那我們就在一個我們有機會發現說它其實在
Another cell in the body is called
身體的另外一個細胞叫做
Granules are tetraneutrophils
顆粒球就是四中性白血球
English called New Show Pair
英文叫New Show Pair
It also performs very well
它表現量也很高
What about this cell?
那這個細胞基本上呢
when it is activated
它受到活化的時候呢
it produces a special phenomenon
它會產生一個特別現象
will generate a structure called Nate
就會產生一個叫做Nate的一個結構
is that it spits out the DNA
就是它會把DNA吐出來
That is, after the cell expands, it will spit out the DNA
就是這個細胞擴大之後它會把DNA吐出來
After spitting it out, its DNA will be sticky
吐出來之後它DNA會當黏
Then stick the bacteria
然後就是黏住細菌
After sticking bacteria
黏住細菌之後呢
it will keep the bacteria expanding
它就會一直細菌的擴展
So the DNA issue you just mentioned is to say
所以你剛剛講的DNA問題就是說
it gets very inflamed in the liver
它在肝臟會發炎很厲害
but just say
但是只說
Suppose you get a bacterial infection
假使你受到一個細菌感染
Then when this infection
然後這個感染的時候
If there are five of them
假使裡面五位存在的時候
In fact, your anti-bacterial effect will be greatly reduced
其實你的這個對抗細菌的效果是會大打折扣的
This is to talk about the importance of public opinion treatment
這個就是講一個民意治療的一個重要性
that is, you have to use the right
就是你要用對
Just like we are using this NTI-TNF to treat
就像我們現在用這個NTI-TNF在治療
This cracking wind is the same as the joint point, what is the consequence?
這個裂風施行關節點一樣 它的後果是什麼
Its price is that it causes tuberculosis
它的代價就是會引起肺結核
so get tuberculosis
所以會結核
So the same, suppose in the future you want the Receptor Tarkey to do this Parsway
所以同樣的 假設將來你要Tarkey這個Receptor做這個Parsway的時候
You may be at risk
你可能要面臨到風險就是說
Do you supercharge certain susceptibility to bacterial infections
你會不會增壓某些對細菌感染的感受性
This is to answer your second question
這是回答你第二個問題
Then why do you say it has something to do with the red savage wolf cabin?
那你說為什麼會跟紅蠻性狼艙有關
you this is what we are doing
你這是我們目前在做
Because the red savage wolf cabin is basically considered to say
因為紅蠻性狼艙基本上被認為說
It is because NUCHOFILIER that net generates too much
它是因為NUCHOFILIER那個net產生過多
So we actually did some experiments
所以我們其實有做過的一些實驗
is when it has too much net
就是當它net過多的時候
It is true that these five bits are a very important factor to control the net structure generated by NUCHOFILIER
它確實這五位是控制NUCHOFILIER產生那個net結構的一個很重要的因子
So ours is a discussion
所以我們那個是一個討論性
If the overproduction of this net is related to 5A
這個net的過度產生都跟5A有關係的話
In the future, it is possible for us to use the 5A of consciousness
那將來我們是有可能透過是意識這個5A
To be aware that this net produces
去意識這個net產生
Then go to realize the sex sac growth of red ants
那進而去意識紅蟻性囊長
This is of course a long-term inference.
這當然是比較長遠的一個推論
basically like this
基本上是這樣
thank you thank you for your question
謝謝你 謝謝你的問題
The first question is also closed on the pre-influenza
第一個問題就是也關在前流感
This is indeed what we have considered
這個確實我們是有考慮到
Its importance in the future of influenza viruses
將來它在流感病毒的重要性
Because of dengue virus it can't have
因為登革病毒它不可能有
The Importance of the Influenza Virus
在流感病毒的重要性
So we in this question
所以我們在這個問題
we are in this problem
我們在這個問題
Because dengue virus it after all the vast majority of people
因為登革病毒它畢竟絕大多數的人
In fact, dengue virus is actually the vast majority of people
其實登革病毒其實絕大多數人
Its symptoms are not obvious
它的症狀都是不明顯的
it really gets serious
它真正會得到很嚴重的
only about 10%
大概只有10%
There will be more serious symptoms
上下等會有比較嚴重的症狀
And most of them are in Taiwan
而且大部分在台灣都是
Older, less resistant
年紀比較大 抵抗力比較弱的
But the flu virus is different
但是流感病毒不一樣
flu virus your symptoms
流感病毒你症狀的
when you are infected
你受到感染的時候
Especially the one that reacts very strongly sometimes
尤其那個有時候反應非常強
so this is really serious
所以這確實是很嚴重
So we use the flu virus
所以我們用流感病毒
Basically the idea is
基本上的想法就是
You just said you didn't do it
你剛剛講沒有做
Because dengue virus has only four lines
因為登革病毒只有四行
That flu virus has so many lines
那流感病毒那麼多行
So let's say we have a flu virus
所以假使說我們對流感病毒
You can also find a common pathway
也能夠找到一個common pathway
Is it possible to realize the western foundation caused by influenza virus
那是不是就可以意識流感病毒造成的西方基礎
it's really what we think
這確實是我們的想法
so we have been doing
所以我們有在做
So our treatment method is basically
所以我們這個做的治療方法基本上是
When I came up with this idea
我當時在做出這個想法的時候
In fact, it subverts the general idea
其實是顛覆一般的想法
Because normally we treat viral infections
因為一般我們要治療病毒感染
The first thought is whether there is a drug
第一個想法就是有沒有一個藥物
able to realize it replicates
能夠意識它複製
it won't copy
它不會複製
it won't have disease
它就不會有疾病
But why something like this
但是為什麼這樣子的東西
challenged for some reason
受到一些挑戰原因
It's because the virus mutates sometimes
是因為因為病毒突變有時候
it will not be healed
它就不會受到醫治
Another reason is that
那另外一個原因就是說
that virus hypothetical
那個病毒假使
when it has entered the body
它已經進到體內的時候
elicit a vocal response
引起發音反應
You are healing the replication and it is too late
你在醫治複製已經來不及了
it's been a lot
它已經很多了
so you just said you didn't say
所以你剛剛講沒有說
we make this drug
我們做這個藥物
Another purpose of doing this research
做這個研究的另外一個目的
really hope to find a virus after infection
確實是希望找到一個病毒感染之後
inside the macroscopic cells
在巨視細胞裡面
A common path that elicits an articulatory response
引起發音反應的共同的一個路徑
Find a cure from hope
從希望那邊找到一個藥來治療
is so
是這樣
Then you obviously know my details.
那你顯然對我的底細打得很清楚
you also know i do this
你還知道我是做這個
There is nothing wrong with K-Z's treatment
K-Z的治療 沒有錯
I actually did this first
其實我最早是做這個
Doing the radiation tumor treatment in various ways
在種種是做那個放射腫瘤治療
For cancer, you use a lot
那癌症 你用很多的
Institute of Cancer Drugs
癌症藥物所
After treatment, there will indeed be more immune responses
處理完之後確實會產生多的免疫反應
including some that can cause allergic reactions
包括有些是會引起過敏反應
some just cause that skin
有些就是會造成那個皮膚
It will itch and hurt
會癢 會有受傷
This base rotation is actually quite interesting
這個的基轉其實是滿有趣
But I haven't researched this field yet
但是我還沒有研究這個領域
but i believe
但是我相信
All of these things are what I'm talking about today
這些所有東西都是跟我今天講的
The circle in the first picture is related
第一張圖那個圓圈圈是有關係的
Because no matter what kind of disease
因為不管什麼樣的疾病
almost always
幾乎都是這樣
it elicits a vocal response
它會引起發音反應
It must be stimulating our body
它一定是刺激我們身體的
a certain partsway
某一個partsway
caused by a receptor
一個受體所引起的
so bless says
所以加持說
Someone is particularly interested in this
有人對這個特別有興趣
He might be able to use something like
他或許可以用類似的方式
go find out
去找出說
After chemotherapy or various medications that we do
我們做的化學藥物治療或各種藥物治療之後
what element does it produce
它到底產生什麼樣的元素
what kind of receptors to stimulate
要刺激什麼樣的受體
Then I believe there is still a lot to be done.
那我相信這還是大有可為的
is possible to find a way to suppress its inflammatory response
是有可能找到一個路徑來抑制它的發炎反應
Hello
你好
I want to ask about this 5A receptor
我想問說這個5A這個受體
It is mainly through which transfer molecule
它主要大概是透過哪一個轉入分子
to open the downstream bacteria
來打開下游的菌
And I saw a slide
還有我看到一張slide
It's written that it activates this NLRP3, the inflammatory payload
它寫說它會活化這個NLRP3這個發炎的負荷體
Then it is through increasing the protein of this load body
那它是透過增加這個負荷體的蛋白
or increase its aggregation
還是說增加它的這個聚合
Then there is another
然後還有一個就是
For this feeling you have about this and that Cyrolyte Dome
針對你對這個那個Cyrolyte Dome的這個感覺
That is to say, it actually said at the beginning
就是說它其實一開始是說
It will first initiate some of the more important Cyrokyne
它會先initiate一些比較主要的Cyrokyne
and then cause the entire
然後再引起整個
Or is it that he turned on the entire Path bit from the beginning?
還是說他一開始就是整個Path位全部都打開
Then all the track cards come out
然後所有的賽道卡也都出來
that's a very good question
這是非常好的問題
That's what we've been doing lately
這也是我們最近在做
That is, since we discovered that many viruses can stimulate 5A
就是我們自從發現很多病毒都會刺激5A之後
We are very interested in his next entry
我們就很有興趣他下有的入境
How is the entry of interest passed on?
興趣入境是怎麼傳的
So the first research we did was to do this inflamed body
所以我們第一個做的研究就是做這發炎體
Because inflammation is now a very important Path bit
因為發炎體現在是非常重要的一個Path位
they have a fever together
他們一起發燒
Denge Fever is actually called Denge Fever
燈閣熱其實為什麼叫燈閣熱
It is because when this patient is infected
就是因為這個病人受到感染的時候
He develops a very bad temperature and a high fever
他會產生非常厲害的溫度不良高會發燒
So we were wondering
所以我們當時是想知道說
Then why does it cause this fever
那為什麼會引起這個發燒
It proves that this path is also taken
就證明也是走這個路徑
Because he has the ability to activate the inflammatory body
因為他下有會活化發炎體
Then will he have any other paths?
那他到底會不會還有什麼樣其他的路徑
this is what we are doing now
這是我們現在正在做的
Because few people did 5A research in the past
因為在過去做5A的研究的人很少
Because I don't know who is on him
因為不知道他上有是誰
Then do this kind of pronunciation response. Many people have studied this message transmission in the past.
那做這種發音反應在過去很多人研究這個訊息傳遞
They are all lions, this lion is provocative and eats you know
他們都獅子這個獅子挑轉的吃你知道
Because they don't like to be a giant cell
因為他們都不喜歡做這個巨勢細胞
What I want to say is that it is very hard for us to do this kind of research
我要講的是說我們做這種研究是很辛苦
We're all going to use mouse cells or human blood cells
我們都是要用老鼠的細胞或是用人類的血液細胞
The reason is because many people are researchers and I also want to use cell pigs
原因是因為很多人做研究師我也要使用細胞豬
Doing Cell Pigs vs. People Doing Research
做細胞豬對做研究的人
good people who do cancer research
做癌症研究的人是很好的
Because cancer is cells that are absent
因為癌症就是不在場的細胞
So a lot of the results with Cellpigs are pretty good
所以用細胞豬做出來的很多結果都很好
we have to react
我們要做這種反應
We bless with a cell pig
我們加持用一個細胞豬來做
when infected with a virus
用病毒感染的時候
It will react like our mouse
它會反應跟我們這個老鼠的
Cellular reaction with human blood
跟人類的那個血液血產生細胞反應
totally different
完全不一樣
So it's really hard for us to do this experiment.
所以我們做這個實驗其實是比較辛苦的
So the questions you just mentioned
所以你剛剛講的那幾個問題
What is its downstream
它下游是靠什麼
We now probably know that it is downstream through SYK
我們現在大概知道說它下游它是透過SYK
Then after passing through the downstream, you will eat a Buddha chair
然後經過那個下游會吃一佛化椅
buddhist tree
佛門樹
But there is a big gap in the middle
但是中間還有一個很大的gap
we don't know
我們不是很清楚
This is the direction of our current research
這是我們現在研究的方向
This is back to what I just said
這也就是回到剛剛我說的
the path of this study
這個研究的路徑
This study is actually a continuation of the work
這個研究其實是一個延續的工作
is endless
是沒有止境的
We are now hoping that before I retire
我們現在就是希望在我退休前
To be able to figure out the dirty path
能夠把這個下流這個路徑搞清楚
Then come again maybe I'll have a chance to be here next time
然後再來或許我下次就有機會在這邊
share my work with you
跟各位分享我的工作
and then be able to give you more clarity
然後能夠給各位更清楚
A more satisfactory answer would be this
更滿意的答案這樣
Thanks
謝謝
Any question
還有問題嗎
ok, may I ask the lady
好 請問這位女士
thank you
謝謝 請教一下
Because I was late just now and there was a miss in front of me
因為我剛剛遲到前面有miss掉
so you might mention
所以您可能提到
maybe i didn't hear you clearly
可能我沒有聽清楚
As for the cause of the inflammation you just mentioned
就您剛講到那個發言的原因
some of them are viruses
是有幾個是病毒的
One of them mentioned is that
其中提到一個是那個
What about urea crystallization?
尿素結晶的情況是吧
i want to understand
我想明白一下
Normally, our urea will crystallize, that's right.
正常講我們尿素會有結晶 沒有錯
But what is causing it to over crystallize?
但是什麼情況是導致它過度結晶呢
can understand
可以了解一下
Thanks
謝謝
Crystallization is of course the first
產生結晶當然第一個
The basic reason is because it
基本原因就是因為它
it's high
它高啦
because it's as high as a
因為它高到一個
Worse than that spiritual point
差那個靈界點
you call it crystallization
你叫它產生結晶
But crystallization occurs in the body
但是在體內會產生結晶
there are many factors
還有很多因素
such as blood circulation
比如說跟血液循環
Because you see where most of Pain likes to be
因為你看痛痛大部分都喜歡在哪裡
like in this
就喜歡在這個
thumbs up
在大拇指嘛
That's because the temperature of the feet is relatively low
那因為腳的溫度比較低
So it is easier to crystallize
所以它比較容易結晶
but there are other factors
但是還有其他的因素
also cause crystallization
也會造成結晶
so
所以
The factors that cause crystallization are actually
造成結晶的因素其實
some people
有些人
still working on
還是在研究
because
因為
Many people have high uric acid
很多人尿酸很高
but it won't gout
但是它就不會痛風
There are also such patients
也有這種病人
it has high uric acid
它尿酸高
but it won't explain
但是它就不會解釋
it won't hurt
它不會痛
so
所以
What other factors determine
到底還有什麼因素在決定
will it be sexual
它會不會出性
it crystallizes
它產生結晶
In addition to the physical factors we know
除了我們知道那些物理的因素之外
Temperature definitely affects beyond its melting point
溫度絕對會影響到它的溶點之外
there are other things we don't know very well
還有的東西我們不是很清楚
I don't know, let me exchange opinions
不曉得我交換一下意見
that's because
就是因為
i do sports nutrition
我做運動營養
that athlete
那那個運動員
because he's doing this
因為他的做這些
this explosive movement
這個爆發力的運動
it produces a lot of halo acids
它產生很多的卤酸
When the haloic acid rises
那血卤酸上升的時候
will decrease
會減少
excretion of uric acid
尿酸的排泄
Normal uric acid will partly come out of our urine
尿酸正常性會有一部分會從我們的尿液裡面擺出
normal situation
正常情形
But it also reduces its excretion
但是還會減少它的排泄
so it builds up in the blood
所以因此它就會在血液裡面累積起來
Therefore, it is more likely for this kind of person to experience pain and collapse.
所以對這種人比較容易發生有痛崩的現象
We say explosive movement
我們說爆發力的運動
What if in this way of speaking
那如果在這種講法的話呢
Then if we exercise too much
那如果當我們運動過多的情形之下
Is it also because some cause some athletes
是不是也是因為有些導致有些運動員
more prone to infection
比較容易有發炎感染
This injury results in permanent sports damage
這種傷害導致永久性的運動傷害
Thanks
謝謝
Although I'm not very...
雖然我不太...
i don't exercise
我沒有運動
My guide is regular exercise
我而指導是常運動
Actually it is
其實是這樣
In fact, after exercising
其實運動完之後
body tissue will be injured
身體組織都會受傷
so many athletes
所以很多運動員
he is actually now
他其實現在
just after exercising
就是運動完之後
He likes to eat that high protein
他都喜歡吃那個高蛋白
because when you are exercising a lot
因為你在大量運動的時候
including your muscles
包括你的肌肉
Muscles do...
肌肉其實都會...
He... our muscles are sore after exercising
他...我們運動完肌肉會酸
In fact, it's a bit...wrong. You just mentioned that the host finished eating.
其實有點...錯你剛剛講到主持人吃完
This is where many of our normal machine packs die
這個是我們很多的正常的機器包會死亡
So you have to eat a lot of albumin and then supplement it
所以你要吃很多那個白蛋白再去把它補充
so you just said nothing wrong
所以你剛剛講完沒有錯
In fact, that is an over-exercise person.
其實那個就是過度運動人的
Because he is the same inside
因為他在體內也是一樣
movement from a certain point of view
運動從某個角度來講
Back to the round one I started with
又回到我一開始的一張圓的
is the constant state
就是恆定狀態
your extreme exercise
你極度的運動
In fact, it is also a pressure on the body
其實對身體也是一個壓力
Stress also produces a so-called steady state
壓力的時候也會產生一個所謂的恆定狀態
So intense exercise can actually produce an inflammatory response
所以很厲害的運動其實也會產生發炎反應
there's nothing wrong with that
這是沒有錯的
so many athletes
所以很多運動員
Many people say athletes are healthy
很多人都說運動員很健康
Actually, go and see that
其實你去看看那個
Explain that athletes do not live longer than average
說明運動員沒有活得比一般人久
They sometimes say that sports cause different injuries
他們有時候常常說運動的時候造成不同的傷害
In fact, it will cause all kinds of occupational injuries
其實會造成各式讓職損傷
So there is no saying that the movement itself is also
所以沒有說運動本身也是
A very important factor that promotes the inflammatory response
促進發炎反應的一個很重要因素
It will accelerate the progress of many diseases
會加速那個很多的疾病的進行
there is another one, right?
還有一本是吧
there are two more
還有兩本
another one
還有一本
has a problem
有問題
You seem to be ready to give me an answer.
你這個好像是套好要做手給我回答的
In my other research, Dean Liu just said that I am also working on a molecule.
我的另外一個研究剛剛劉院長講我就是也在做一個分子
How he put this giant cell it has two types
他如何把這個巨式細胞它有兩型
It is M1, which is the inflammation of the blood-spraying multi-cell technology that I just mentioned
就是M1就是我剛剛所說的噴血多細胞技術發炎
But another one called M2 basically it's anti-inflammatory
但是另外一個叫M2基本上它是抗發炎
we did
這個我們確實也做過
We have done a study
我們有做過一篇研究
We have done research and used this flu virus to trigger Diuchen's severe inflammation.
我們有做研究就是一樣用這個流感病毒去引丟臣厲害的發炎反應
And then we'll just beat that protein in
然後我們就把那個蛋白質打進去
Just like you say it makes M1 become M2
就是就像你講它就讓M1變成M2
It is true that its entire inflammatory response is reduced.
那確實它整個發炎反應就下降
Then its death rate also decreased
然後它死亡率就也有下降
So if your family is interested
所以你家是有興趣的話
Give me the memory film, I can show you the Payback meter
記憶膜給我 我可以把那Payback計給你看
really works
確實是有效
are we the last question
我們是不是最後一個問題
department
要科系喔
and a copy of that scientific magazine
還有一本那個科學人雜誌
still me
還是我一位
Oh, good
喔好
I just talked a lot about the loss of immunity
剛剛有談了不少那個免疫的失控
The sky cannon window and the sky cannon window
那個天炮窗跟類天炮窗
Is there any new progress in these two current materials or research?
這兩個現在資料上或者研究上有沒有什麼新的進展
i didn't do my homework sorry
我沒有做功課 對不起
Sky gun window in English is Penfix
天炮窗的英文就是Penfix
You are asking a good question. Wenyongs here belongs to the P department.
你這問得很好 文勇這邊這個是屬於P科
Ji Biwen has an expert in the P department here, that is our Liu Wuyan miscellaneous
吉碧文這邊就有P科的專家就是我們劉烏焰雜
right
對不對
Liu Wuyan can study Penfix's current Treatment
劉烏焰長可以研究Penfix現在的Treatment
no fact
沒有事實上
I mean, it's an autoimmune disease.
就是說這個是一個自身免疫的病
So it has nothing to do with the cell base storm
所以跟細胞基數的風暴倒沒有什麼關係
But it's also about immunity
但是也是跟免疫有關
so far
所以目前為止
There really aren't that many good self-disciplines
好的自法確實不是那麼多
That is to rely on the inner stock market
那就是也是要靠內股城
Inner stock market or this method of suppressing the immune response
內股城或是抑制免疫反應的這種方法
over there
那邊的話
how to use this
在怎麼樣利用這種
How does this immune system cause autoimmunity
這種對免疫怎麼樣造成自身免疫
Then treat according to that mechanism
然後根據那個機制來治療
In fact there is still a lot of room
事實上還有很多空間
So there's a lot more in immunology
所以在免疫學上還有很多
can be discussed
可以去探討的
and find some way
而且找出一些方式
Because these students and teachers just said in the past
因為過去剛剛這些學生老師也講過
It is said that it is done by the inner stock city
說是用內股城來做的話
He takes the good and the bad
他把好的壞的都拿掉
that's not the best way
那並不是最好的方式
But the method so far is to use
但是目前為止的方法還是用
A high amount of domestic stock market will do it
高量的內股城來做
right
對
In fact, the disease can be suppressed
事實上是可以把這個疾病壓下來
But let me analyze
但是跟大家分析一下
very interesting
很有趣的
like i talk a little too much
好像我講太多一點
Today the protagonist is
今天主角是
now to say
現在要說
It's just that we have a treatment that's not the best
就是我們有一個治療方法並不是最好
it's not enough by itself
它本身不夠
But it can reduce the amount of internal memory used
但是它可以把用內部存的量降低的
is called IVIG
是叫做IVIG
Just take that person's immigrant globulin
就是把那個人的immigrant globulin
Just look at it's in the blood
就是看這是血裡面的
it is going to
它是要把
In the case of a company, 100, 300, or thousands of people will be
公司的話就會把100個、300個、上千個人的
The immigrant globulin is separated from Dong Nei's blood
董內出來的血裡面分出來它的immigrant globulin
is imcanti
就是imcanti
No, it's IGG
不是,是IGG
then hit the patient
然後砸給病人
I don't know why
這個話不曉得什麼原因
It's going to stop this autoimmune reaction
它會意志住這種自身免疫反應
it can be done over there
那邊是可以它的
current thinking says
目前的想法說
It has something to do with the biological blood of that sugar
那邊跟那個糖的生物血也有點關係
it can will
它可以意志
That is the autoimmunity
那個就是這個自身免疫
right
對
good
好
Yes or no
是不是
to the scientific man magazine
給這位科學人雜誌
can share with him
可以跟他分享
another one
還有一本
there is none left
沒有了
OK
OK
It does not matter
那沒關係
we are
我們就是
come again or continue
再來還是繼續開
keep talking
繼續講
let me ask
我請問一下
that cell storm theory
那個細胞風暴理論
Is there any correlation for an antioxidant
有沒有相關對於一個抗氧化
especially this one
是尤其的這個
chicken flower
雞花
please advise on this
請教一下這一點
Actually in the pronunciation response
其實在發音反應
one of the features
其中一個特徵
I just said that inside Cytogenetic Storm
我剛剛說細胞氣素風暴裡面
One of them includes free muscle
其中一個就有包括自由肌
free muscle
就是自由肌
so free muscle
所以自由肌
In fact, it also caused many
其實也是造成很多
a cause of cell damage
細胞損傷的一個原因
because it's a lot
因為它大量
After becoming a free muscle
成成自由肌之後
it will spray water
它就會跟噴到水
it becomes a whole desoiled
它就變成一整個脫土
it oxidizes many things
它就把很多東西氧化
So it also causes
所以它也是造成
cause of injury
受傷的原因
So in the past it was said
所以在過去曾經有人說
Anti-free muscle drugs
用抗自由肌的藥物
in anti-inflammatory
在抗發炎
it works
它是有效的
But it only works for that
但是它只能夠對那個
mild inflammation
輕度的發炎
it will work
它會有效
But for cell-based storms so severe
但是對細胞基礎風暴這麼嚴重
That is, its strength compared to the cell base
就是它的強度跟細胞基礎比起來
it's much weaker
它是弱很多啦
So just relying on free machines
所以光是要靠自由機器
To treat such a powerful technological storm
去治療這麼厲害的技術風暴
The effect is probably very limited
效果大概是非常有限的
Okay, thank you
好 謝謝
ok i think this speech will end here
好我想這次演講就到這裡結束
then we thank you again
那我們再次謝謝
Thank you professor for your excellent speech
謝謝教授非常精采的演講
thank you all thank you
謝謝各位 謝謝各位
Thanks
謝謝